<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="./_c74_ref.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!--This file has been automatically generated by Doctor Max. DO NOT EDIT THIS FILE DIRECTLY.-->

<c74object name="bach.zsearch" module="bach">

	<digest>
		Search for Z-related pitch-class sets
	</digest>

	<description>
		Performs a search for families of pitch-class sets having the
	</description>

	<!--METADATA-->
	<metadatalist>
		<metadata name="author">bachproject</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">bach</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">bach objects</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">bach set theory</metadata>
	</metadatalist>

	<!--INLETS-->
	<inletlist>
		<inlet id="0" type="INLET_TYPE">
			<digest>
				Cardinality of Pitch Class Sets
			</digest>
			<description>
			</description>
		</inlet>
		<inlet id="1" type="INLET_TYPE">
			<digest>
				Modulo
			</digest>
			<description>
			</description>
		</inlet>
	</inletlist>

	<!--OUTLETS-->
	<outletlist>
		<outlet id="0" type="INLET_TYPE">
			<digest>
				Z-Families
			</digest>
			<description>
				The output list has one parenthesis level for each cardinality
				and then one parenthesis level for Z-Family. This means that all the
				pitch-class sets sharing the same (multi-)interval vector are gathered
				together in a subllll.
			</description>
		</outlet>
		<outlet id="1" type="INLET_TYPE">
			<digest>
				Relative Interval Vectors
			</digest>
			<description>
				The shape of this list refers to the shape of the output Z-Families:
				a single (multi-)interval vector is output for each family
			</description>
		</outlet>
	</outletlist>

	<!--ARGUMENTS-->
	<objarglist>
		<objarg name="modulo" optional="1" type="int">
			<digest>
				Modulo
			</digest>
			<description>
				In the standard framework, the modulo is the number of subdivision of the octave (represented as a circle). The modulo is thus the number of
				points in this circle. The default and most common modulo is 12 (corresponding to semitonal grid). Modulo 24 is the quartertone grid, and so on.
				<br /> <br />
			</description>
		</objarg>
		<objarg name="subsetscardinality" optional="1" type="int">
			<digest>
				Subsets Cardinality
			</digest>
			<description>
				Cardinality of the test subsets. See the <m>subsetscardinality</m> attribute.
			</description>
		</objarg>
	</objarglist>

	<!--MESSAGES-->
	<methodlist>
		<method name="all">
			<arglist />
			<digest>
				Trigger prime form search for all cardinalities
			</digest>
			<description>
				An <m>all</m> message triggers prime form search for all cardinalities and outputs the results.
				<br />				See also:<m>llll</m><br />
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="bang">
			<arglist />
			<digest>
				Perform the last search
			</digest>
			<description>
				Perform the search on the most recently received input data.
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="int">
			<arglist />
			<digest>
				Set modulo
			</digest>
			<description>
				An integer in the right inlet will set the modulo. <br /> <br />
				In the standard framework, the modulo is the number of subdivision of the octave (represented as a circle). The modulo is thus the number of
				points in this circle. The default and most common modulo is 12 (corresponding to semitonal grid). Modulo 24 is the quartertone grid, and so on.
				<br /> <br />
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="llll">
			<arglist />
			<digest>
				Trigger prime form search for given cardinalities
			</digest>
			<description>
				A single number k will trigger the search for all prime forms of cardinality k.
				A couple of numbers, say [m n], will trigger the search for all cardinailties from m to n and output the result
				<br />				See also:<m>all</m><br />
			</description>
		</method>
	</methodlist>

	<!--ATTRIBUTES-->
	<attributelist>
		<attribute name="group" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1">
			<digest>
				Group
			</digest>
			<description>
				The group according to which we consider the prime forms. <br /> <br />
				In Set Theory, two pitch-class sets are often considered to be "the same" when they are linked by the action of some simple transformation.
				For instance, the sets <b>0 1 4</b> and <b>2 3 6</b> are linked by a transposition of 2 (corresponding, on the clock diagram, to a rotation of 2 steps).
				Such "simple transformations" usually form a group. One thus usually needs to choose a group to determine a framework; this group will entail
				the concept of "copy" of a pitch-class set: which is any other pitch-class set obtained by the action of a transformation of the group.
				For instance, if our group is the group of transposition, <b>2 3 6</b> is a copy of <b>0 1 4</b>, and viceversa. <br />
				The most common groups of such form in increasing nesting are: <br />
				- the group of transposition: formed by all the transposition by a certain amount, and there are only 12 transposition if our modulo is 12, or
				in general n transposition if our modulo is n (the mathemathicians would say that such group is isomorphic to the cyclic group Z_n).
				For instance, a C major chord is the same as a D major chord, with respect to this group, but it is NOT the same as a C minor chord. <br />
				- the group of transposition and inversions: formed by all the transposition of the previous group, plus all the combination of such transposition with
				inversions, i.e. reflection with respect to any axis on the clock diagram. If our modulo is n, this group has 2n elements (the mathemathicians
				would say that such group is isomorphic to the dihedral group D_n).
				For instance, a C major chord is the same as a D major chord, with respect to this group, and also the same as a C minor chord. <br />
				- the affine group of transposition, inversions, and multiplications: this group (here things get a little bit more complicated...) is formed
				by all the elements of the previous group plus we add the transformation multiplying each pitch class by a certain number k (prime with the modulo).
				Classical multiplications, with modulo = 12, are M_5 (multiplication by 5) and M_7 (multiplication by 7).
				For instance, our <b>0 4 7</b> C major chord is the same as <b>0 8 11</b>, since 5 * (0 4 7) = (0 20 35) = (0 8 11). <br />
				Up to the group of transposition and inversion, the interval vector of a pitch-class set is preserved. The affine group does not preserve the interval vector.
				<br /> <br />
			</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="label" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="Group" />
				<attribute name="paint" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1" value="1" />
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="enumindex" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="mode" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1">
			<digest>
				Mode
			</digest>
			<description>
				Criterion according to which the prime forms are chosen. <br /> <br />
				The prime form is always defined to be the "smallest" copy of a given set. This definition depends on the ordering one chooses.
				Two ordering are supported by bach: <br />
				<m>Lexicographic</m>: the prime form is the "smallest" copy of the set lexicographically (numbers are compared left to right).
				For instance <b>0 1 5 11</b> is preferred to <b>0 6 7 8</b>. <br />
				<m>Compactness First</m>: the lexicographic clause is secondary: primarily the prime form is chosen among the "most compact" prime forms,
				For instance <b>0 6 7 8</b> is preferred to its transposed <b>0 1 5 11</b>, although it is not preferred to its other transposed <b>0 1 2 6</b>.
				<br /> <br />
			</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="label" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="Mode" />
				<attribute name="paint" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1" value="1" />
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="enumindex" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="modulo" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1">
			<digest>
				Modulo
			</digest>
			<description>
				The modulo of the diagram. <br /> <br />
				In the standard framework, the modulo is the number of subdivision of the octave (represented as a circle). The modulo is thus the number of
				points in this circle. The default and most common modulo is 12 (corresponding to semitonal grid). Modulo 24 is the quartertone grid, and so on.
				<br /> <br />
			</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="label" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="Modulo" />
				<attribute name="paint" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1" value="1" />
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="text" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="out" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1">
			<digest>
				Outlet Types
			</digest>
			<description>
				The <m>out</m> attribute is a sequence of characters identifying the outlet types (one character for each llll outlet). Characters can be one of the following: <br />
				<m>n</m> (default): 'native' output: faster and more precise between bach objects, but unreadable by standard Max objects (an "bach.llll" message appears instead). <br />
				<m>t</m>: 'text' output: slower and limited in size, but readable by standard Max objects. A plain llll in text format is a generic Max message.
				To keep the representation invertible (i.e., to allow a bach object receiving a text-format llll to interpret it exactly as if it was native format,
				except for the size limitation), some specific kinds of symbols are preceded by a backtick: namely, symbols containing parens, or containing textual
				representations of numbers or pitches, or beginning with a backtick, plus the symbols "null" and "nil" (distinct from the reserved words
				"null" and "nil" representing the empty list and the empty sublist) are preceded by a backtick. Moreover, the symbols "int", "float" or "list"
				are preceded by a backtick only if they are the first element of an llll, to distinguish them from the corresponding reserved messages of Max. <br />
				<m>m</m>: 'max' output: mostly equivalent to the "t" specifier, but no symbol is backticket except "int", "float" and "list" at the beginning of an llll.
				It is important to notice that, differently from text-format lllls proper, Max-format lllls might not be invertible even if they do not reach the size
				limit for Max message. This means that a bach object receiving a Max-format llll output from another bach object might interpret it differently
				from the original, or in some cases might even reject it. <br />
				<m>x</m>: disabled output (nothing is output) <br />
				<m>p</m>: 'portal' output: only used by bach.portal to intercept the @out attribute specified while creating the abstraction (see bach.portal). <br />
				The native output is recommended, unless communication with standard Max messages is needed.
				Disabling unused outputs can be useful if extreme optimization of the patch is needed.
				<br /> <br />
			</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="category" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="Behavior" />
				<attribute name="label" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="Outlet Types" />
				<attribute name="paint" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1" value="1" />
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="text" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="periodiconce" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1">
			<digest>
				Count Periodic Subsets Once
			</digest>
			<description>
				Some particular periodic subsets might be counted more than once while computing (multi-)interval vectors.
				For instance: in (0 1 6), the set {0, 6} might be counted both as {0, 6} and as {6, 12}.
				If you don't want this, just set this attribute.
				Usually one does not want to count twice this occurrence (and the other occurrences
				of periodic sets, if cardinality > 2), thus by default the attribute is set.
			</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="label" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="Count Periodic Subsets Once" />
				<attribute name="paint" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1" value="1" />
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="onoff" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="subsetscardinality" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1">
			<digest>
				Subset Cardinality
			</digest>
			<description>
				Cardinality of the test subsets. A generalized Z-search looks for equalities
				of the multi-interval vectors. In general the (multi-)interval vector counts the number
				of copies of the prime form of a certain cardinality which one can find in the original set:
				for instance the standard interval vector is a 2-vector, i.e. counts how many copies of sets like
				{0, 1} or {0, 4} are contained in the original sets (no wonder this numbers are exactly the number of
				semitones or major third one can find among the notes of the set). But this is true for any
				cardinality: we might ask which is the trichordal content of a vector, thus testing how many copies
				of sets like {0, 1, 2} or {0, 2, 5} are contained in the set. This number is the cardinality
				of this family of test sets. This is by default 2 (yielding the interval vector).
				If you want a k-vector (multi-interval analysis) change this number to k.
			</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="label" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="Subset Cardinality" />
				<attribute name="paint" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1" value="1" />
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="text" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="zfamiliesmincard" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1">
			<digest>
				Minimum Cardinality in a Z-Family
			</digest>
			<description>
				Minimum cardinality for a Z-family to be output. If this number is N,
				and the algorithm finds M prime forms sharing the same (multi-)interval vector,
				those prime forms are output only if M>=N. Typically this attribute is 2, meaning that
				if a prime form has no Z-partners (another prime form sharing the same (multi-)interval vector)
				it will not be output, and only really Z-related pitch-class sets are output.
			</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="label" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="Minimum Cardinality in a Z-Family" />
				<attribute name="paint" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1" value="1" />
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="text" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
	</attributelist>

	<!--DISCUSSION-->
	<discussion>
		Z-relation relies on the concept of "copies" and thus on the concept of group action. <br /> <br />
	</discussion>

	<!--SEEALSO-->
	<seealsolist>
		<seealso name="bach.ifunc" />
		<seealso name="bach.primeform" />
		<seealso name="bach.circle" />
		<seealso name="bach.ivec" />
		<seealso name="bach.pcsetinfo" />
		<seealso name="bach.mod+" />
		<seealso name="bach.mod-" />
		<seealso name="bach.modtimes" />
	</seealsolist>

	<misc name = "Input">
		<entry name ="Inlet 1 (int)">
			<description>
				Cardinality of Pitch Class Sets.
			</description>
		</entry>
		<entry name ="Inlet 2 (int)">
			<description>
				Modulo.
			</description>
		</entry>
	</misc>

	<misc name = "Output">
		<entry name ="Outlet 1 (llll)">
			<description>
				Z-Families.
				The output list has one parenthesis level for each cardinality
				and then one parenthesis level for Z-Family. This means that all the
				pitch-class sets sharing the same (multi-)interval vector are gathered
				together in a subllll.
			</description>
		</entry>
		<entry name ="Outlet 2 (llll)">
			<description>
				Relative Interval Vectors.
				The shape of this list refers to the shape of the output Z-Families:
				a single (multi-)interval vector is output for each family
			</description>
		</entry>
	</misc>

	<misc name = "Discussion">
		<entry name ="More details">
			<description>
		Z-relation relies on the concept of "copies" and thus on the concept of group action. <br /> <br />
			</description>
		</entry>
		<entry name ="Keywords">
			<description>
Z-relation, pitch-class, set, search, find, k-deck, copy, group, action, transposition, inversion, prime form, normal form, family, interval vector.
			</description>
		</entry>
	</misc>

</c74object>