<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="./_c74_ref.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!--This file has been automatically generated by Doctor Max. DO NOT EDIT THIS FILE DIRECTLY.-->

<c74object name="bach.lookup" module="bach" kind="patcher">

	<digest>
		Return specific elements of an llll (inlets reversed)
	</digest>

	<description>
		Returns one or more specific elements of an llll, based on their addresses.
		It works exactly like <o>bach.nth</o>, but with reversed inlets.
	</description>

	<!--METADATA-->
	<metadatalist>
		<metadata name="author">bachproject</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">bach</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">bach abstractions</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">bach llll</metadata>
	</metadatalist>

	<!--INLETS-->
	<inletlist>
		<inlet id="0" type="INLET_TYPE">
			<digest>
				Address llll
			</digest>
			<description>
			</description>
		</inlet>
		<inlet id="1" type="INLET_TYPE">
			<digest>
				llll to retrieve elements from
			</digest>
			<description>
			</description>
		</inlet>
	</inletlist>

	<!--OUTLETS-->
	<outletlist>
		<outlet id="0" type="INLET_TYPE">
			<digest>
				Retrieved elements
			</digest>
			<description>
			</description>
		</outlet>
	</outletlist>

	<!--ARGUMENTS-->
	<objarglist>
		<objarg name="original" optional="1" type="llll">
			<digest>
				llll to retrieve elements from
			</digest>
			<description>
				A default llll to retrieve elements from can be set as <o>bach.lookup</o>'s argument.
			</description>
		</objarg>
	</objarglist>

	<!--MESSAGES-->
	<methodlist>
		<method name="bang">
			<arglist />
			<digest>
				Repeat last operation
			</digest>
			<description>
				Returns the requested elements according to the most recently received lllls.
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="llll">
			<arglist />
			<digest>
				Function depends on inlet
			</digest>
			<description>
				An llll in first inlet sets the address of the elements to extract, extract such elements and
				outputs them.
				An llll in second inlet sets the llll from which elements should be extracted.
				An address is an llll providing a unique representation of the position of an element in another llll.
				It is a concept shared by many bach object.
				The address of each element of an llll's root level is simply its position counting from 1.
				The address of an element in a sublist is a list composed by the position of the element in the sublist,
				preceded by the position of the sublist in the parent llll,
				and so on up to the root level, as a sort of "path" to the element.<br />
				For instance, given the llll <b>a b c (d e (f g) h i) j k</b> the position of <b>c</b> is <b>3</b>;
				the position of <b>(d e (f g) h i)</b> is <b>4</b>;
				the position if <b>e</b> is <b>4 2</b> since to reach it it takes to go to the 4th element of the root level, which is a sublist,
				and to the 2nd element of that sublist.
				By reading the address from right to left, it can be seen that this is equivalent to saying
				that the pointed element is the 2nd of the 4th.
				Likewise, in the above llll <b>f</b> has the address <b>4 3 1</b> since it is the 1st of the 3rd of the 4th.<br />
				In addition, addresses sent to bach objects can contain negative positions,
				that is positions counted from the end of the llll instead than the right.
				Negative and positive positions can be safely mixed within a single address.
				Thus, the address of the element <b>g</b> can be expressed as <b>4 3 2</b> as well as <b>4 3 -1</b> or <b>-3 -3 -1</b>.<br />
				<b>bach.lookup</b> also accepts a special syntax to indicate multiple elements of one level of the llll:
				a sublist in the address will be interpreted as a sequence of elements in the corresponding level.
				In this way, the address <b>4 (2 4 5)</b> means "the 2nd, 4th and 5th of the 4th", that is <b>e h i</b>.
				Negative positions are accepted here as well.
				Any number after the multiple-element sublist in the address llll is ignored.<br />
				The multiple-element sublist can contain sublists in its turn. These are called "range sublists".
				A range sublist is composed by two positions, and indicates all the elements comprised between these two positions.
				Either or both positions of a range sublist can be negative.
				So, the address <b> 4 ((2 -1) 1)</b> means "From the 2nd to the last (i.e. the 1st from the right) and the 1st of the 4th",
				that is <b>e (f g) h i d</b>.
				As a tip, notice that to retrieve all the contents of a sublist (as opposed to the sublist itself)
				the range (1 -1) can be specified.
			</description>
		</method>
	</methodlist>

	<!--ATTRIBUTES-->
	<attributelist>
		<attribute name="nils" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1">
			<digest>
				
			</digest>
			<description>
				When set to 1, if no element was present at the requested address <b>()</b> is output.
				When set to 0 (default), <b>null</b> is output.
			</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="nil for Not Found" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="out" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1">
			<digest>
				Outlet Types
			</digest>
			<description>
				The <m>out</m> attribute is a sequence of characters identifying the outlet types (one character for each llll outlet). Characters can be one of the following: <br />
				<m>n</m> (default): 'native' output: faster and more precise between bach objects, but unreadable by standard Max objects (an "bach.llll" message appears instead). <br />
				<m>t</m>: 'text' output: slower and limited in size, but readable by standard Max objects. A plain llll in text format is a generic Max message. To keep the representation invertible (i.e., to allow a bach object receiving a text-format llll to interpret it exactly as if it was native format, e
			</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="category" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="Behavior" />
				<attribute name="label" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="Outlet Types" />
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="text" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="unwrap" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1">
			<digest>
				Unwrap
			</digest>
			<description>
				When set to 1, the outermost couple of parentheses of any sublist to be output is removed.
				For instance, if the llll <b>a b (c d e)</b> is input and its third element is requested,
				<b>c d e</b> will be output instead of <b>(c d e)</b>.
				Defaults to 0.
			</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="label" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="Unwrap" />
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="onoff" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
	</attributelist>

	<!--DISCUSSION-->
	<discussion>
		The abstraction is a small abstraction of <o>bach.nth</o>.
	</discussion>

	<!--SEEALSO-->
	<seealsolist>
		<seealso name="bach.nth" />
		<seealso name="bach.pick" />
	</seealsolist>

	<misc name = "Input">
		<entry name ="Inlet 1 (llll)">
			<description>
				Address llll.
			</description>
		</entry>
		<entry name ="Inlet 2 (llll)">
			<description>
				llll to retrieve elements from.
			</description>
		</entry>
	</misc>

	<misc name = "Output">
		<entry name ="Outlet 1 (llll)">
			<description>
				Retrieved elements.
			</description>
		</entry>
	</misc>

	<misc name = "Discussion">
		<entry name ="More details">
			<description>
		The abstraction is a small abstraction of <o>bach.nth</o>.
			</description>
		</entry>
		<entry name ="Keywords">
			<description>
retrieve, look up, element, address.
			</description>
		</entry>
	</misc>

</c74object>