<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="./_c74_ref.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!--This file has been automatically generated by Doctor Max. DO NOT EDIT THIS FILE DIRECTLY.-->

<c74object name="bach.ezmidiplay" module="bach" kind="patcher">

	<digest>
		Quick way to play MIDI
	</digest>

	<description>
		Converts the data coming from the playout of <o>bach.roll</o> or
		<o>bach.score</o> into a MIDI stream, and plays it.
	</description>

	<!--METADATA-->
	<metadatalist>
		<metadata name="author">bachproject</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">bach</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">bach abstractions</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">bach notation</metadata>
	</metadatalist>

	<!--INLETS-->
	<inletlist>
		<inlet id="0" type="INLET_TYPE">
			<digest>
				The llll coming from <o>bach.roll</o> or <o>bach.score</o> playout
			</digest>
			<description>
				The expected llll must be formatted in the playout syntax (it is such by default if you link
				the playout of <o>bach.roll</o> or <o>bach.score</o> to the first <o>bach.ezmidiplay</o> inlet). <br /> <br />
				For <o>bach.roll</o>, the playout syntax is used whenever the information about a note or chord is sent through the playout (either at playtime
				or at offline play, or selection dump).
				The playout syntax is a slight variation of the standard chord gathered syntax. Two different cases apply, according to the <m>playmode</m>
				attribute value. If the <m>playmode</m> is set to Chordwise, the information about each chord is output in the form <br />
				<b>chord <m>voice_number</m> <m>MIDI_channel</m> (<m>onset</m> <m>NOTE1</m> <m>NOTE2</m> <m>NOTE3</m> <m>chord_flag</m>) </b> <br />
				where each <b><m>NOTE</m></b> is the gathered syntax of the note (see below).
				If the <m>playmode</m> is set to Notewise, information about each note is output as if the note were the only note in the chord, i.e. in the form <br />
				<b>note <m>voice_number</m> <m>MIDI_channel</m> (<m>onset</m> <m>NOTE</m> <m>chord_flag</m>) </b> <br />
				where <b><m>NOTE</m></b> is the note gathered syntax.
				The <m>MIDI_channels</m> is the one associated with the voice to which the note or chord belongs. The <m>onset</m> is in milliseconds,
				The <m>chord_flag</m> is a bitfield summing values of 1 (if chord is locked), 2 (if chord is muted), 4 (if chord is solo). <br />
				The playout syntax also concerns markers: they are output in the form: <b>marker <m>NAME_OR_NAMES</m> <m>onset_ms</m> <m>role</m> <m>optional:content</m></b>
				where the <m>NAME_OR_NAMES</m> is either a single atom (if the marker has a single name) or a wrapped plain llll containing the names, and the <m>optional:content</m>
				is only output if the marker role requires it.
				<br /> <br />
				In <o>bach.roll</o>, one can assign a role for each marker, so that they can represent elements such as
				time signatures, tempi, barline, measure divisions. Time signature markers and tempi markers
				also require a "content", i.e. an llll specifying the time signature or the tempo.
				When adding a marker via the <m>addmarker</m> message, the role can be specified as third parameter,
				and the content as fourth parameter. Alternatively, roles and content can be set via the marker inspector.
				Roles can be: <br />
				<m>Time Signature</m>: set by the symbol "timesig", it represents a time signature, and expects the time signature llll as content.
				For instance, a message to add such a marker could be <b>addmarker 0 foo timesig (4 4)</b>.<br />
				<m>Tempo</m>: set by the symbol "tempo", it represents a time signature, and expects the tempo llll as content (tempo figure and tempo
				value). For instance, a message to add such a marker could be <b>addmarker 0 foo tempo (1/8 50)</b>, meaning
				that the tempo is 1/8 = 50.<br />
				<m>Measure Barlines</m>: set by the symbol "barline", it represents a barline, and expects no content.
				For instance, a message to add such a marker could be <b>addmarker 0 foo barline</b>. <br />
				<m>Measure Division</m>: set by the symbol "division", it represents a measure division, and expects no content.
				For instance, a message to add such a marker could be <b>addmarker 0 foo division</b>. <br />
				<m>Measure Subdivision</m>: set by the symbol "subdivision", it represents a measure subdivision, and expects no content.
				For instance, a message to add such a marker could be <b>addmarker 0 foo subdivision</b>. <br />
				All these marker can be parsed by bach.quantize in order to automatically retrieve the measureinfo of the
				entire bach.roll.
				<br /> <br />
				For <o>bach.roll</o>, the gathered syntax for any note is, in its simplest form <b>(<m>pitch_cents</m> <m>duration</m> <m>velocity</m> <m>note_flag</m>)</b>
				where <m>pitch_cents</m> is the pitch of the note in MIDI cents, the <m>duration</m> is measured in milliseconds, the <m>velocity</m>
				is a value from 1 to 127 corresponding to the note dynamic, and
				the <m>note_flag</m> is an optional bitfield summing values of 1 (if note is locked), 2 (if note is muted), 4 (if note is solo). <br />
				In its most general form, each note can have different specifications and attributes, defining
				graphics, pitch breakpoints, slots, names.
				Each of these specifications is done in the form <b>(<m>specification_name</m> <m>SPECIFICATION CONTENT</m>)</b>, and must be put after the <m>velocity</m>
				and before the <m>note_flag</m>. The order in which the specifications are listed is, on the other hand, irrelevant. For instance, a note definition might have the form
				<b>(7300. 136. 127 (graphic 7400 -1/2) (slots (1 (0. 0. 0.) (0.294118 81.138889 0.) (0.294118 38.805556 0.) (1. 0. 0.))) (name pippo) 0 )</b>
				<br /> <br />
				Instead of MIDIcents (or cents), one can also instert pitches.
				The syntax for the single note must be an unique symbol (no spaces) with:
				<b><m>notename</m>-<m>optional:accidental</m>-<m>octave_number</m></b>.
				Dashes are only set in order to separate parts of the symbol, but must not be included in the symbol. <br /> <br />
				Names are in anglo-saxon syntax ("C", "D", "E"...), and are case insentitive. Middle C is C5.
				They and should be immediately followed by the possible accidentals and the
				octave number, without any space (e.g. <b>D#4</b>). <br />
				Accidentals are: <b>#</b> (sharp), <b>b</b> (flat), <b>x</b> (double sharp), <b>q</b> (quartertone sharp), <b>d</b> (quartertone flat),
				<b>^</b> (eighth-tone sharp), <b>v</b> (eighth-tone flat)
				One can also extend the accidental by setting a rational specification followed by a <b>t</b>. For instance <b>C5+1/16t</b> is
				middle C, 1/16 tone up.
				<br /> <br />
				The <m>graphic</m> specification informs about the enharmonicity status of a note.
				It is given by an llll in the form <b>(<m>graphic</m> <m>displayed_midicents_ignoring_accidental</m> <m>displayed_accidental</m>)</b>,
				where <m>displayed_midicents_ignoring_accidental</m> are the cents of the diatonic displayed note (ignoring any accidental that it might have),
				and <m>displayed_accidental</m> is the displayed accidental in rational form (sharp corresponding to 1/2, flat to -1/2, quarterflat to -1/4 and so on).
				For instance, a Db just above the middle C would have a graphic specification of <b>(graphics 6200 -1/2)</b>.
				<br /> <br />
				The <m>breakpoint</m> specification informs about possible pitch breakpoints that a note duration line has. This is useful to represent glissandi.
				It is given by an llll in the form <b>(<m>breakpoints</m> <m>BPT1</m> <m>BPT2</m> <m>BPT3</m>...)</b>,
				where each <m>BPT</m> is an llll in the form <b>(<m>relative_x_position</m> <m>delta_midicents</m> <m>slope</m>)</b>, where
				<m>relative_x_position</m> is a double precision number from 0 to 1 representing the point where the breakpoint is, 0 corresponding to
				the notehead and 1 corresponding to the note tail; <m>delta_midicents</m> is the pitch difference (in midicents) between the breakpoint pitch and the base note pitch;
				<m>slope</m> is a value from -1 to 1 corresponding to the curvature of the segment of duration line preceding the breakpoint (this implies that the slope of the first breakpoint
				is always ignored), as for Max <o>curve</o> object (thus 0 being linear). <br />
				Two breakpoints are always present: the first breakpoint corresponds always to (0 0 0), and can never
				be different than this; the last breakpoint corresponds always to the note tail, and must always be in the form <b>(1 <m>delta_midicents</m> <m>slope</m>)</b>.
				If all breakpoints are trivial (thus if there are just two breakpoints: notehead and tail, and the notetail has <m>delta_midicents</m> = 0), the breakpoint
				specification is never given as output. For instance, a note making a glissando upwards and then downwards of 200cents, linear while ascending and exponential in the descent,
				will have the breakpoint specification of the form <b>(breakpoints (0 0 0) (0.5 200 0) (1 0 0.5))</b>. <br />
				If the <m>breakpointshavevelocity</m> attribute is set to 1, pitch breakpoints also have velocities, thus the complete <m>BPT</m> specification is in the form
				(<m>relative_x_position</m> <m>delta_midicents</m> <m>slope</m> <m>velocity</m>),
				where <m>velocity</m> is a number from 1 to 127 corresponding to the pitch breakpoint dynamic. If different breapoints have different dynamics, the behavior of
				the velocity between them is considered to be interpolatory, for instance by abstractions like <o>bach.dl2line</o> or <o>bach.dl2curve</o>.
				<br /> <br />
				The <m>slots</m> specification informs about the content of each one (or a subset) of the slots of a note.
				It is given by an llll in the form <b>(slots <m>SLOT1</m> <m>SLOT2</m>...)</b>,
				where each one of the <m>SLOT</m> is an llll containing the information about one slot, in the form
				<b>(<m>slot_number</m> <m>SLOT_CONTENT</m>)</b>. <br />
				The slot content syntax depends on the slot type. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>function</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>POINT1</m> <m>POINT2</m> <m>POINT3</m>...</b> where each
				<m>POINT</m> is in turn in the form <b>(<m>x</m> <m>y</m> <m>slope</m>)</b>, where the first two elements are the coordinates of the point, and the last one is
				a slope parameter, from -1 to 1, corresponding to the curvature of the segment preceding the point. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>int</m> or <m>float</m> the content must be in the simplest form: <b><m>number</m></b>. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>intlist</m> or <m>floatlist</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>number1</m> <m>number2</m>...</b>. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>text</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>text_as_an_unique_symbol</m></b>. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>llll</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>WRAPPED_LLLL</m></b>, equivalent to <b>(<m>LLLL</m>)</b>.  <br />
				- For slot of type <m>filelist</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>filepath1</m> <m>filepath2</m> <m>filepath3</m>... <m>active_file_index</m></b>,
				where <m>active_file_index</m> is the index of the file which will appear as clicked (active). <br />
				- For slot of type <m>spat</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>SPATPOINT1</m> <m>SPATPOINT2</m> <m>SPATPOINT3</m>...</b> where each
				<m>SPATPOINT</m> is in turn in the form <b>(<m>t</m> <m>radius</m> <m>angle</m> <m>interpolation_type</m>)</b>,
				where the first element is the time position (by default, if the domain is temporal, this is between 0 and 1), then comes the radius
				(distance of the sound from the listener) and the angle which the sound makes with respect to a reference vertical direction.
				Last parameter is an interpolation type, which is 0 (default) for circular spatialization and 1 for linear spatialization. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>color</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>red</m> <m>green</m> <m>blue</m> <m>alpha</m></b>, where
				the parameters are the components of the RGBA color representation (from 0. to 1.).  <br />
				- For slot of type <m>3dfunction</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>POINT1</m> <m>POINT2</m> <m>POINT3</m>...</b> where each
				<m>POINT</m> is in turn in the form <b>(<m>x</m> <m>y</m> <m>z</m> <m>slope</m>)</b>, where the first three elements are the coordinates of the point, and the last one is
				a slope parameter, from -1 to 1, corresponding to the curvature of the segment preceding the point. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>filter</m>, when you need to input content you can use the syntax:
				<b><m>filtertype</m> <m>cutoff_frequency_Hz</m> <m>gain_dB</m> <m>Q_or_slope</m></b>, where <m>filtertype</m> is one of the following symbols:
				<m>lowpass</m>, <m>highpass</m>, <m>bandpass</m>, <m>bandstop</m>, <m>peaknotch</m>, <m>lowshelf</m>, <m>highshelf</m>, <m>allpass</m>.
				You can equivalently use for input the syntax
				<b><m>a0</m> <m>a0</m> <m>a2</m> <m>b1</m> <m>b2</m></b>, where the parameters are the coefficients of a biquad filter, as for <o>biquad~</o>.
				Finally, when data is output, the syntax is always a combination of the two:
				<b><m>a0</m> <m>a0</m> <m>a2</m> <m>b1</m> <m>b2</m> (<m>filtertype</m> <m>cutoff_frequency_Hz</m> <m>gain_dB</m> <m>Q_or_slope</m>)</b>. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>dynfilter</m> the content must be in the form: <b>(<m>t1</m> <m>FILTER1</m>) (<m>t2</m> <m>FILTER2</m>) (<m>t3</m> <m>FILTER3</m>)...</b>, where
				each <m>FILTER</m> is in the form defined for slot of type <m>filter</m>, just above. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>articulations</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>art1</m> <m>art2</m>...</b>, i.e. a sequence of
				articulations introduced as symbols.
				The list of the are standard available articulations as symbols is: "staccato" or "stacc", "staccatissimo" or "staccmo",
				"fermata" or "ferm", "portato" or "por", "accent" or "acc", "accentstaccato" or "accstacc", "accentportato" or "accport",
				"portatostaccato" or "portstacc", "martellato" or "mart", "martellatostaccato" or "martstacc", "lefthandpizzicato" or "lhpiz",
				"trill" or "tr", "gruppetto" or "grupp", "upmordent" or "umord", "downmordent" or "dmord", "doublemordent" or "mmord",
				"upbowing" or "ubow", "downbowing" or "dbow", "tremolo3" or "trem3" (for the tremolo with three slashes), "tremolo2" or "trem2"
				(for the tremolo with two slashes), "tremolo1" or "trem1" (for the tremolo with a single slash).
				Notice that the default bach font has all the articulations glyphs; however, not all the other supported fonts do,
				in particular Boulez doesn't have a certain number of the previous articulations among its glyphs.
				If you don't see an articulation as you wish
				(e.g. tremoli with Boulez), it might be because the font doesn't have the proper character, so try to use another font.
				Articulation symbols can also be retrieved by hovering on the corresponding element in the slot window. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>notehead</m> the content must a single notehead symbol.
				The list of the standard available noteheads as symbols is: "default", "doublewhole", "whole", "white", "black", "diamond", "cross", "plus",
				"none", "accent", "blacksquare", "whitesquare", "square" "blacktriangle", "whitetriangle", "triangle", "blackrhombus", "whiterhombus", "rhombus".
				In <o>bach.score</o>, the "square", "triangle" and "rhombus" notehead are black or white depending on the note duration; in <o>bach.roll</o> only
				the black flavour is used.
				As for articulations, not all fonts support all symbols.
				Notehead symbols can also be retrieved by hovering on the corresponding element in the slot window. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>togglematrix</m>, <m>intmatrix</m> or <m>floatmatrix</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>WRAPPED_MATRIX_AS_LLLL</m></b>,
				equivalent to <b>(<m>ROW1</m> <m>ROW2</m>...)</b>, where each row is a wrapped llll.
				In the bach environment, a matrix is just a llll having depth two, whose first-level sublllls are the rows of the matrix.
				For instance the matrix <b>(1 0 0) (0 1 0) (0 0 1)</b> is the 3 by 3 identity matrix. A "good" matrix is supposed to be well formed,
				i.e. all its rows must have the same length. A matrix is square if the length of the rows (which is the number of columns) is the same
				as the number of rows.
				<br /> <br />
				The <m>name</m> specification informs us about a possible name (or possibles names) of a notation item.
				It is simply given by an llll in the form <b>(name <m>NAME_OR_LLLL_OF_NAMES</m>)</b>,
				where <m>NAME_OR_LLLL_OF_NAMES</m> is either a single of symbols or integer, or an llll corresponding to the name(s) of the notation item.
				For instance, an item named as "john george" will correspond to the llll <b>(name john george)</b>.
				An item named "(high 1) (low 2)" will correspond to the llll <b>(name (high 1) (low 2))</b>.
				If an element has no names, the <m>name</m> specification is never given as output.
				<br /> <br />
				For <o>bach.score</o>, the playout syntax is used whenever the information about a note or chord is sent through the playout (either at playtime
				or at offline play, or selection dump).
				The playout syntax is a slight variation of the standard chord gathered syntax. Two different cases apply, according to the <m>playmode</m>
				attribute value. If the <m>playmode</m> is set to Chordwise, the information about each chord is output in the form <br />
				<b>chord <m>voice_number</m> <m>MIDI_channel</m> (<m>symbolic_duration</m> <m>duration_ms</m> <m>symbolic_onset_in_measure</m>
				<m>onset_from_score_beginning_in_ms</m> <m>NOTE1</m> <m>NOTE2</m> <m>NOTE3</m> <m>chord_flag</m>) </b> <br />
				where each <b><m>NOTE</m></b> is the gathered syntax of the note.
				If <m>playrest</m> is set to 1, and the chord is a rest, the router symbol is <b>rest</b> instead of chord. <br />
				If the <m>playmode</m> is set to Notewise, information about each note is output as if the note were the only note in the chord, i.e. in the form <br />
				<b>note <m>voice_number</m> <m>MIDI_channel</m> (<m>symbolic_duration</m> <m>duration_ms</m> <m>symbolic_onset_in_measure</m>
				<m>onset_from_score_beginning_in_ms</m> <m>NOTE</m> <m>note_flag</m>) </b> <br />
				where <m>NOTE</m> is the note gathered syntax. <br />
				If <m>playrest</m> is set to 1, and the chord is a rest, the router symbol is <b>rest</b> instead of chord, and there is no <m>NOTE</m> llll. <br />
				In case the played note or chord is just a grace chord, the <m>symbolic_duration</m> becomes an llll in the form <b>(g <m>grace_symbolic_duration</m>)</b>.
				The <m>MIDI_channels</m> is the one associated with the voice to which the note or chord belongs. The <m>onset</m> is in milliseconds,
				The <m>chord_flag</m> is a bitfield summing values of 1 (if chord is locked), 2 (if chord is muted), 4 (if chord is solo). <br />
				The playout syntax also concerns markers: they are output in the form: <b>marker <m>NAME_OR_NAMES</m> <m>ONSET</m> none</b>
				where the <m>NAME_OR_NAMES</m> is either a single atom (if the marker has a single name) or a wrapped llll containing the names.
				The last <b>none</b> symbol is the marker role, currently unsupported in <o>bach.score</o>. The <m>ONSET</m> can either be a single
				floating point value, representing the onset in milliseconds (if the marker is attached to the milliseconds position), or an llll representing
				the onset timepoint (if the marker is attached to the position inside the measure). <br />
				The playout syntax also concerns tempi: they are output in the form <b>tempo <m>voice_number</m> <m>tempo</m> <m>TEMPO_LLLL</m></b>,
				where <m>tempo</m> is the floating point tempo referred to the quarter note, and
				<m>TEMPO_LLLL</m> is in the form <b>(<m>tempo_figure</m> <m>tempo_value</m> <m>tempo_sym_onset</m> <m>interpolation_to_next?</m>)</b>.
				If the tempo starts an accelerando/rallentando (i.e. interpolation is set to 1), then the <m>tempo</m> element is substituted by the llll
				<b>(<m>tempo</m> <m>next_tempo</m> <m>interp_duration_ms</m>)</b>.  <br />
				The playout syntax also concerns measures: if <m>playmeasures</m> is 1, at the beginning of each measure (for each voice), an llll is output
				in the form <b>measure <m>voice_number</m> <m>measure_number</m> <m>MEASUREINFO_LLLL</m></b>.
				If a tempo and/or a chord lie at the beginning of a measure, the order of output for the elements is: measure, tempo, chord (or notes). <br />
				For all the previously exposed cases, if the <m>playoutfullpath</m> attribute is set to 1, the <m>voice_number</m> is substituted by
				an llll determining the address of the element (see the <m>playoutfullpath</m> attribute for more information. <br /> <br />
				A timepoint represents a given instant inside <o>bach.score</o>, as a measure-attached position.
				It identifies such point according to a measure, a position inside such measure,
				and possibly a voice (in case tempi and time signatures are not synchronous for all voices).
				Differently from absolute millisecond positions,
				timepoints are represented by lllls, in one of the following syntaxes: <br />
				- <b>(<m>measure_number</m>)</b>: represents the point is at the beginning of the measure identified by the introduced measure number, in the first voice.
				For instance, <b>(4)</b> represents the point at the very beginning of measure 4, voice 1. <br />
				- <b>(<m>measure_number</m> <m>sym_onset_in_measure</m>)</b>: represents the point inside the measure identified by the introduced measure number (in the first voice),
				but not necessarily at the beginning, rather at the generic position in measure identified by the symbolic onset <m>sym_onset_in_measure</m>.
				For instance, <b>(4 1/4)</b> represents the point at measure 4, voice 1, after 1/4 from the beginning of the measure. <br />
				- <b>(<m>voice_number</m> <m>measure_number</m> <m>sym_onset_in_measure</m>)</b>: represents the point inside the measure identified by the introduced measure number,
				in the voice identified, by the introduced voice number, at the generic position in measure identified by the symbolic onset <m>sym_onset_in_measure</m>.
				For instance, <b>(2 4 1/4)</b> represents the point at measure 4, voice 2, after 1/4 from the beginning of the measure. Specifying voice numbers explicitly is especially
				important if voices don't have the same tempi or time signatures.
				<br />
				A timepoint can also  be specified via a <b>(<m>float_measure_number</m>)</b>, representing the point in a floating
				point position between two measures (referred to the first voice). For instance, <b>(4.2)</b> represents the point at the 20% of measure 4, voice 1.
				Furthermore, the <m>sym_onset_in_measure</m> can be replaced by a float between 0 and 1 to represent a point between the beginning (0) and the end
				of the measure (1); for instance <b>(1 4 0.2)</b> represents the point after 20% of measure 4, voice 1.
				<br />
				If the measure number is replaced by the <b>any</b> symbol, then the following rational is interpreted as a global symbolic onset inside the score.
				For instance, <b>(any 27/4)</b> represents the point at 27/4 after the beginning of the score, referred to the measureinfo of voice 1;
				<b>(3 any 27/4)</b> does the same for voice 3.
				<br /> <br />
				For <o>bach.score</o>, the gathered syntax for any note is, in its simplest form <b>(<m>pitch_cents</m> <m>velocity</m> <m>tie?</m> <m>note_flag</m>)</b>
				where <m>pitch_cents</m> is the pitch of the note in MIDI cents, the <m>velocity</m>
				is a value from 1 to 127 corresponding to the note dynamic, the <m>tie?</m> value is 1 only if the note starts a tie and 0 otherwise, and
				the <m>note_flag</m> is an optional bitfield summing values of 1 (if note is locked), 2 (if note is muted), 4 (if note is solo). <br />
				In its most general form, each note can have different specifications and attributes, defining one of the possible extras:
				graphics, pitch breakpoints, slots, names, articulations.
				Each of these specifications is done in the form <b>(<m>specification_name</m> <m>SPECIFICATION CONTENT</m>)</b>, and must be put after the <m>tie?</m>
				and before the <m>note_flag</m>. The order in which the specifications are listed is, on the other hand, unimportant. For instance, a note definition might have the form
				<b>(7000. 127 1 (graphic 6900 1/2) (slots (1 (0. 112.5 0.) (1. 0. 0.))) (articulation stacc) (name foo) 0)</b>.
				<br /> <br />
				The <m>graphic</m> specification informs about the enharmonicity status of a note.
				It is given by an llll in the form <b>(<m>graphic</m> <m>displayed_midicents_ignoring_accidental</m> <m>displayed_accidental</m>)</b>,
				where <m>displayed_midicents_ignoring_accidental</m> are the cents of the diatonic displayed note (ignoring any accidental that it might have),
				and <m>displayed_accidental</m> is the displayed accidental in rational form (sharp corresponding to 1/2, flat to -1/2, quarterflat to -1/4 and so on).
				For instance, a Db just above the middle C would have a graphic specification of <b>(graphics 6200 -1/2)</b>.
				<br /> <br />
				The <m>breakpoint</m> specification informs about possible pitch breakpoints that a note duration line has. This is useful to represent glissandi.
				It is given by an llll in the form <b>(<m>breakpoints</m> <m>BPT1</m> <m>BPT2</m> <m>BPT3</m>...)</b>,
				where each <m>BPT</m> is an llll in the form <b>(<m>relative_x_position</m> <m>delta_midicents</m> <m>slope</m>)</b>, where
				<m>relative_x_position</m> is a double precision number from 0 to 1 representing the point where the breakpoint is, 0 corresponding to
				the notehead and 1 corresponding to the note tail; <m>delta_midicents</m> is the pitch difference (in midicents) between the breakpoint pitch and the base note pitch;
				<m>slope</m> is a value from -1 to 1 corresponding to the curvature of the segment of duration line preceding the breakpoint (this implies that the slope of the first breakpoint
				is always ignored), as for Max <o>curve</o> object (thus 0 being linear). <br />
				Two breakpoints are always present: the first breakpoint corresponds always to (0 0 0), and can never
				be different than this; the last breakpoint corresponds always to the note tail, and must always be in the form <b>(1 <m>delta_midicents</m> <m>slope</m>)</b>.
				If all breakpoints are trivial (thus if there are just two breakpoints: notehead and tail, and the notetail has <m>delta_midicents</m> = 0), the breakpoint
				specification is never given as output. For instance, a note making a glissando upwards and then downwards of 200cents, linear while ascending and exponential in the descent,
				will have the breakpoint specification of the form <b>(breakpoints (0 0 0) (0.5 200 0) (1 0 0.5))</b>. <br />
				If the <m>breakpointshavevelocity</m> attribute is set to 1, pitch breakpoints also have velocities, thus the complete <m>BPT</m> specification is in the form
				(<m>relative_x_position</m> <m>delta_midicents</m> <m>slope</m> <m>velocity</m>),
				where <m>velocity</m> is a number from 1 to 127 corresponding to the pitch breakpoint dynamic. If different breapoints have different dynamics, the behavior of
				the velocity between them is considered to be interpolatory, for instance by abstractions like <o>bach.dl2line</o> or <o>bach.dl2curve</o>.
				<br /> <br />
				The <m>slots</m> specification informs about the content of each one (or a subset) of the slots of a note.
				It is given by an llll in the form <b>(slots <m>SLOT1</m> <m>SLOT2</m>...)</b>,
				where each one of the <m>SLOT</m> is an llll containing the information about one slot, in the form
				<b>(<m>slot_number</m> <m>SLOT_CONTENT</m>)</b>. <br />
				The slot content syntax depends on the slot type. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>function</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>POINT1</m> <m>POINT2</m> <m>POINT3</m>...</b> where each
				<m>POINT</m> is in turn in the form <b>(<m>x</m> <m>y</m> <m>slope</m>)</b>, where the first two elements are the coordinates of the point, and the last one is
				a slope parameter, from -1 to 1, corresponding to the curvature of the segment preceding the point. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>int</m> or <m>float</m> the content must be in the simplest form: <b><m>number</m></b>. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>intlist</m> or <m>floatlist</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>number1</m> <m>number2</m>...</b>. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>text</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>text_as_an_unique_symbol</m></b>. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>llll</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>WRAPPED_LLLL</m></b>, equivalent to <b>(<m>LLLL</m>)</b>.  <br />
				- For slot of type <m>filelist</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>filepath1</m> <m>filepath2</m> <m>filepath3</m>... <m>active_file_index</m></b>,
				where <m>active_file_index</m> is the index of the file which will appear as clicked (active). <br />
				- For slot of type <m>spat</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>SPATPOINT1</m> <m>SPATPOINT2</m> <m>SPATPOINT3</m>...</b> where each
				<m>SPATPOINT</m> is in turn in the form <b>(<m>t</m> <m>radius</m> <m>angle</m> <m>interpolation_type</m>)</b>,
				where the first element is the time position (by default, if the domain is temporal, this is between 0 and 1), then comes the radius
				(distance of the sound from the listener) and the angle which the sound makes with respect to a reference vertical direction.
				Last parameter is an interpolation type, which is 0 (default) for circular spatialization and 1 for linear spatialization. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>color</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>red</m> <m>green</m> <m>blue</m> <m>alpha</m></b>, where
				the parameters are the components of the RGBA color representation (from 0. to 1.).  <br />
				- For slot of type <m>3dfunction</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>POINT1</m> <m>POINT2</m> <m>POINT3</m>...</b> where each
				<m>POINT</m> is in turn in the form <b>(<m>x</m> <m>y</m> <m>z</m> <m>slope</m>)</b>, where the first three elements are the coordinates of the point, and the last one is
				a slope parameter, from -1 to 1, corresponding to the curvature of the segment preceding the point. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>filter</m>, when you need to input content you can use the syntax:
				<b><m>filtertype</m> <m>cutoff_frequency_Hz</m> <m>gain_dB</m> <m>Q_or_slope</m></b>, where <m>filtertype</m> is one of the following symbols:
				<m>lowpass</m>, <m>highpass</m>, <m>bandpass</m>, <m>bandstop</m>, <m>peaknotch</m>, <m>lowshelf</m>, <m>highshelf</m>, <m>allpass</m>.
				You can equivalently use for input the syntax
				<b><m>a0</m> <m>a0</m> <m>a2</m> <m>b1</m> <m>b2</m></b>, where the parameters are the coefficients of a biquad filter, as for <o>biquad~</o>.
				Finally, when data is output, the syntax is always a combination of the two:
				<b><m>a0</m> <m>a0</m> <m>a2</m> <m>b1</m> <m>b2</m> (<m>filtertype</m> <m>cutoff_frequency_Hz</m> <m>gain_dB</m> <m>Q_or_slope</m>)</b>. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>dynfilter</m> the content must be in the form: <b>(<m>t1</m> <m>FILTER1</m>) (<m>t2</m> <m>FILTER2</m>) (<m>t3</m> <m>FILTER3</m>)...</b>, where
				each <m>FILTER</m> is in the form defined for slot of type <m>filter</m>, just above. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>articulations</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>art1</m> <m>art2</m>...</b>, i.e. a sequence of
				articulations introduced as symbols.
				The list of the are standard available articulations as symbols is: "staccato" or "stacc", "staccatissimo" or "staccmo",
				"fermata" or "ferm", "portato" or "por", "accent" or "acc", "accentstaccato" or "accstacc", "accentportato" or "accport",
				"portatostaccato" or "portstacc", "martellato" or "mart", "martellatostaccato" or "martstacc", "lefthandpizzicato" or "lhpiz",
				"trill" or "tr", "gruppetto" or "grupp", "upmordent" or "umord", "downmordent" or "dmord", "doublemordent" or "mmord",
				"upbowing" or "ubow", "downbowing" or "dbow", "tremolo3" or "trem3" (for the tremolo with three slashes), "tremolo2" or "trem2"
				(for the tremolo with two slashes), "tremolo1" or "trem1" (for the tremolo with a single slash).
				Notice that the default bach font has all the articulations glyphs; however, not all the other supported fonts do,
				in particular Boulez doesn't have a certain number of the previous articulations among its glyphs.
				If you don't see an articulation as you wish
				(e.g. tremoli with Boulez), it might be because the font doesn't have the proper character, so try to use another font.
				Articulation symbols can also be retrieved by hovering on the corresponding element in the slot window. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>notehead</m> the content must a single notehead symbol.
				The list of the standard available noteheads as symbols is: "default", "doublewhole", "whole", "white", "black", "diamond", "cross", "plus",
				"none", "accent", "blacksquare", "whitesquare", "square" "blacktriangle", "whitetriangle", "triangle", "blackrhombus", "whiterhombus", "rhombus".
				In <o>bach.score</o>, the "square", "triangle" and "rhombus" notehead are black or white depending on the note duration; in <o>bach.roll</o> only
				the black flavour is used.
				As for articulations, not all fonts support all symbols.
				Notehead symbols can also be retrieved by hovering on the corresponding element in the slot window. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>togglematrix</m>, <m>intmatrix</m> or <m>floatmatrix</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>WRAPPED_MATRIX_AS_LLLL</m></b>,
				equivalent to <b>(<m>ROW1</m> <m>ROW2</m>...)</b>, where each row is a wrapped llll.
				In the bach environment, a matrix is just a llll having depth two, whose first-level sublllls are the rows of the matrix.
				For instance the matrix <b>(1 0 0) (0 1 0) (0 0 1)</b> is the 3 by 3 identity matrix. A "good" matrix is supposed to be well formed,
				i.e. all its rows must have the same length. A matrix is square if the length of the rows (which is the number of columns) is the same
				as the number of rows.
				<br /> <br />
				The <m>name</m> specification informs us about a possible name (or possibles names) of a notation item.
				It is simply given by an llll in the form <b>(name <m>NAME_OR_LLLL_OF_NAMES</m>)</b>,
				where <m>NAME_OR_LLLL_OF_NAMES</m> is either a single of symbols or integer, or an llll corresponding to the name(s) of the notation item.
				For instance, an item named as "john george" will correspond to the llll <b>(name john george)</b>.
				An item named "(high 1) (low 2)" will correspond to the llll <b>(name (high 1) (low 2))</b>.
				If an element has no names, the <m>name</m> specification is never given as output.
				<br /> <br />
				The <m>articulation</m> specification informs us about an articulation assigned either to a chord or to a note.
				It is simply given by an llll in the form <b>(articulation <m>ARTICULATION_OR_LIST_OF_ARTICULATIONS</m>)</b>,
				where <m>ARTICULATION_OR_LIST_OF_ARTICULATIONS</m> is a list of symbols idenfitying articulations to be added to the notation item.
				The symbols of the list are allowed to be the following ones: "staccato" or "stacc", "staccatissimo" or "staccmo",
				"fermata" or "ferm", "portato" or "por", "accent" or "acc", "accentstaccato" or "accstacc", "accentportato" or "accport",
				"portatostaccato" or "portstacc", "martellato" or "mart", "martellatostaccato" or "martstacc", "lefthandpizzicato" or "lhpiz",
				"trill" or "tr", "gruppetto" or "grupp", "upmordent" or "umord", "downmordent" or "dmord", "doublemordent" or "mmord",
				"upbowing" or "ubow", "downbowing" or "dbow", "tremolo" or "trem" (for the tremolo with three slashes), "tremolo2" or "trem2"
				(for the tremolo with two slashes), "tremolo1" or "trem1" (for the tremolo with a single slash), "gruppetto" or "grupp". <br />
				The default bach font has all the articulations glyphs; however, not all the other supported fonts do, especially Boulez doesn't have
				a certain number of the previous articulations among its glyphs. If you don't see an articulation as you wish
				(e.g. tremoli with Boulez), it might be because the font doesn't have the proper character, so try to use another font.
				<br /> <br />
				Measureinfo is the information about time signature and tempo, plus some other optional specifications concerning the measure itself.
				This can be a single <b><m>TIME_SIGNATURE</m> <m>TEMPO</m></b> valid for all voices and all measures, or a llll containing for each measure and each voice
				an llll in the form <b>(<m>TIME_SIGNATURE</m> <m>TEMPO_OR_LIST_OF_TEMPI</m> <m>SPECIFICATION1</m> <m>SPECIFICATION2</m>...)</b>.
				All elements except for the <m>TIME_SIGNATURE</m> are optional. <br /> <br />
				The <m>TIME_SIGNATURE</m> is an llll containing the measure time signature, in one of the following forms: <br />
				- <b>(<m>numerator</m> <m>denominator</m>)</b> for standard time signatures. For instance, <b>(4 4)</b> corresponds to a 4/4 time signature. <br />
				- <b>((<m>numerator1</m> <m>numerator2</m> <m>numerator3</m>...) <m>denominator</m>)</b> for time
				signatures where the numerator is a sum of numbers.For instance <b>((3 2 3) 8)</b>
				corresponds to a (3+2+3)/8 time signature. <br /> <br />
				The <m>TEMPO_OR_LIST_OF_TEMPI</m> represent in its simplest form, a single tempo. <br />
				A tempo, defined for a measure of a <o>bach.score</o> has one of the following syntaxes: <br />
				- <b>(<m>tempo_value</m>)</b> will assign a quarter tempo at the beginning of the measure. For instance <b>(60)</b> will set a 1/4 = 60 tempo. <br />
				- <b>(<m>tempo_figure</m> <m>tempo_value</m>)</b> will assign the tempo value to the specified symbolic unit (at the beginning of the measure).
				The <m>tempo_figure</m> is indeed the tempo symbolic unit: for instance <b>(3/8 40)</b> will set a tempo of a dotted quarter = 40.<br />
				- <b>(<m>tempo_figure</m> <m>tempo_value</m> <m>tempo_sym_onset</m>)</b> will assign the tempo value to the specified symbolic unit and will put the
				tempo at the point inside the measure specified by the <m>tempo_sym_onset</m>. For instance <b>(3/8 40 1/4)</b> will set a tempo of a dotted quarter = 40
				but not at the beginning of the measure, rather after 1/4 from the beginning.<br />
				- <b>(<m>tempo_figure</m> <m>tempo_value</m> <m>tempo_sym_onset</m> <m>interpolation_to_next?</m>)</b> will do exactly as the previous case
				but if <m>interpolation_to_next?</m> is non-zero it will also toggle the interpolation from this tempo to the following one,
				yielding an accelerando or rallentando (depending if the next tempo is faster or slower). For instance <b>(3/8 40 1/4 1)</b>
				will set a tempo of a dotted quarter = 40, after 1/4 from the beginning, and will toggle the tempo interpolation to next tempo.<br />
				If more than one tempo need to be assigned to a given measure, one needs to use the general syntax for <m>TEMPO_OR_LIST_OF_TEMPI</m>, which is
				<b>(<m>TEMPO1</m> <m>TEMPO2</m> <m>TEMPO3</m>...)</b>, where each tempo must be in one the forms explained above. As an example, consider
				<b>((60) (1/4 70 1/16) (1/8 60 1/8 1) (1/8 80 3/8))</b>, where four tempi have been defined. The order of tempi is irrelevant,
				only their onset is accounted for. <br />
				Also, one might add an integer number at the beginning of each measure llll to indicate that the given measureinfo reference is valid for a
				certain number of measures, such as <b>(<m>how_many_measures</m> <m>TIME_SIGNATURE</m> <m>TEMPO_OR_LIST_OF_TEMPI</m> <m>SPECIFICATION1</m> <m>SPECIFICATION2</m>...)</b>.
				For instance <b>(5 (4 4) ((80) (1/4 160 1/2)))</b> creates 5 measures of 4/4, each one starting with quarter = 80, and then each one accelerating
				until 1/4 = 160 exactly at half of the measure. For instance
				<b> (((4 4) (1/8 60)) ((2 4) (1/4 50 1/4 1)) (4 (4 4)) (nil (180)))</b> means that we start a bar 1 in 4/4 and octave note = 60, then we
				pass at 2/4 and quarter = 50 after 1/4 of measure 2, and at that moment, an accelerando starts. The accelerando lasts during 4 4/4-measures,
				and then ends at the following measure on a new tempo of quarter = 180. <br /> <br />
				Each <m>SPECIFICATION</m> is an optional llll representing a given measure parameter, in the form <b>(<m>parameter_name</m> <m>parameter_value</m>)</b>.
				The <m>parameter_name</m> is a symbol identifying the parameter. The complete list of parameters symbols and their corresponding
				values is the following one: <br />
				- <b>width</b>: assigns a fixed width to a measure. It expects as value a fixed width in pixels that the measure will have (referred to the default
				vertical and horizontal zoom of 100%, and modified accordingly to those). Assigning a <m>width</m> parameter will also lock the measure barline,
				so that the width will remain the same, no matter how many chords and notes the measure does and will contain. Use the "auto" symbol
				instead of the fixed width to revert to the automatic measure width assignment (depending on the measure content). <br />
				- <b>widthfactor</b>: assigns a local factor for the spacing. It expects as value a multiplier factor, which will be applied to the whole measure
				spacing, and which will compress (for values less than 1) or expand (for values
				greater than 1) the width of the measure and the spacing of its chords accordingly. In this case, the measure barline is not locked, only the
				width factor is changed. <br />
				- <b>barline</b>: assigns a specific ending barline to a given measure. It expects a specific letter, representing the barline type. This letter
				can be one of the following ones: 'a' = automatic barline (defaul), 'n' = normal barline, 'd' = dashed barline, 'p' = dotted barline (p = "points"),
				't' = double barline (t = "two"), 's' = solid barline, 'f' = final barline, 'h' = hidden barline. <br />.
				- <b>shownumber</b>: deals with measure numbers. If an "off" symbol is given as value, it means that the measure number of the current measure will
				not be displayed. If a specific number is given, it will be assigned as a forced measure number to be displayed, for instance <b>(shownumber -4)</b> will
				show -4 as measure number (also see the attribute <m>measurenumberoffset</m>). If an "auto" symbol is given, it will show the measure's automatically
				assigned measure number (default). <br />
				- <b>boxes</b>: assign custom beaming boxes. It expects custom beaming boxes for the measure, as a plain list of rational numbers.
				Custom boxing allows you to handle beam grouping inside the measure differently than beat-wise.
				Each number of the expected list is the symbolic width of each beaming box inside the measure.
				If the given boxes don't fill the whole measure, the last one is padded. For instance, in a 4/4 measure,
				<b>(boxes 1/8)</b> will simply use eight 1/8-wide boxes to beam elements inside the measure, instead of the default 1/4 wide ones (beats).
				This is equivalent to <b>(boxes 1/8 1/8 1/8 1/8 1/8 1/8 1/8 1/8)</b>.
				Analogously, <b>(boxes 1/2 1/8 1/4 1/8)</b> is a more exotic boxing for the same time signature. <br />
				As a final example, (((4 4) (60) (widthfactor 0.5) (barline h) (shownumber off))) for a given measure sets a 4/4 time signature, a quarter = 60 tempo,
				compresses the measure by a factor of two, hides its final barline and its number.
				<br /> <br />
			</description>
		</inlet>
		<inlet id="1" type="INLET_TYPE">
			<digest>
				Messages to <o>noteout</o>
			</digest>
			<description>
				Send in the third inlet all the messages that you want to send directly to the <o>noteout</o>
				inside the abstraction, such as the MIDI port.
			</description>
		</inlet>
	</inletlist>

	<!--OUTLETS-->
	<outletlist>
		<outlet id="0" type="INLET_TYPE">
			<digest>
				The list containing MIDI triplets
			</digest>
			<description>
				Triplets of MIDI data in the form <b><m>MIDI_note</m> <m>velocity</m> <m>MIDI_channel</m></b>.
				where <m>MIDI_note</m> is not in midicents, but in MIDI values (60 = middle C), <m>velocity</m> is the MIDI
				velocity (0 to 127, 0 being note-off), and <m>MIDI_channel</m> is of course the MIDI channel.
				For each note, a note-on and a note-off list is properly sent.
			</description>
		</outlet>
		<outlet id="1" type="INLET_TYPE">
			<digest>
				Number of available channels
			</digest>
			<description>
				The number of channels which could actually be used by the user (ignoring the percussion 10th channel),
				the other ones being used to handle microtonality (see <m>int</m> method for more information).
			</description>
		</outlet>
	</outletlist>

	<!--ARGUMENTS-->
	<objarglist>
		<objarg name="tonedivision" optional="1" type="int">
			<digest>
				Microtonal division
			</digest>
			<description>
				Number of division of the tone of the equal temperament needed. For standard semitonal
				temperament, this is 2 (default); for quartertonal temperament this is 4, and so on.
			</description>
		</objarg>
	</objarglist>

	<!--MESSAGES-->
	<methodlist>
		<method name="adjustpitchbend">
			<arglist />
			<digest>
				Properly assign pitch bend values to MIDI channels
			</digest>
			<description>
				Pitch bend values for MIDI channels are automatically assigned when you introduce the microtonal
				division, and at the object instantiation. Nevertheless, should you touch the pitch bend values elsewhere
				in the patch, the <m>adjustpitchbend</m> message is a shortcut to set again the pitch bend of each channel
				to the needed value for the proper microtonal MIDI playing.
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="clock">
			<arglist />
			<digest>
				Select a clock source
			</digest>
			<description>
				The word <m>clock</m>, followed by the name of an existing <m>setclock</m> objects, sets the <o>bach.ezmidiplay</o>
				object to be controlled by that <m>setclock</m> object rather than by Max's internal millisecond clock.
				The word <m>clock</m> by itself sets the <o>bach.ezmidiplay</o> object back to using Max's regular millisecond clock.
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="int">
			<arglist />
			<digest>
				Set microtonal division, output free MIDI channel number
			</digest>
			<description>
				An integer in the second inlet sets the desired microtonal division. By default this is
				2 (semitonal division), but this can be different: in this case, <o>bach.ezmidiplay</o> automatically maps the
				data on multiple MIDI channels handled with different pitch bend in order to reproduce the microtonal finesse.
				In other words, the object keesp for himself a certain number of channels (which will be affected by the pitch bend),
				and which thus should not be used by the user. <br />
				When the microtonal division changes (and also at the instantiation) the number of free MIDI channels is
				output from the second outlet. If the microtonal division is semitonal, this number will be 15, since it doesn't
				count the channel 10, dedicated to percussions. This means that we can use 15 independent channels to play
				semitonal music. Otherwise, the number will represent the number of MIDI channels which were not used to mimic
				the microtonal instrument. For instance, for quartertonal division (4), this will be 7, since 7 quartertonal channels
				are indeed mapped on 14 real channels; and we could not map 8 of them, since that would yield 16 real channels, whereas
				we just had 15 (not counting percussion channel). Analogously, If we need to play sixth-tonal divisions,
				the number of free channels will be 5 (each channel has to be mapped on 3 channels, 5*3 = 15).
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="list">
			<arglist />
			<digest>
				Send messages to <o>noteout</o>
			</digest>
			<description>
				A list in the first inlet is expected to be in the <o>noteout</o>-like syntax: <b>(<m>pitch</m> <m>velocity</m> <m>MIDIchannel</m>)</b>
				where, on the other hand, the <m>pitch</m> is expected to be in MIDIcents (and not as MIDI number). The velocity must range from 1 to 127,
				a velocity of 0 is considered as a note-off. <br />
				A list in the third inlet is automatically sent to the <o>noteout</o> object contained in the
				abstraction. You might want to use this to define, for instance, the MIDI port. Refer to the <o>noteout</o>
				documentation to know more.
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="llll">
			<arglist />
			<digest>
				Convert into MIDI data and play
			</digest>
			<description>
				<o>bach.ezmidiplay</o> expects the lllls coming from the playout of a <o>bach.roll</o>
				or <o>bach.score</o> (standard plain <o>noteout</o> syntax is also accepted, provided that pitch is given
				in MIDIcents; refer to the <m>list</m> message to know more).
				It will convert such syntax them in MIDI triplets with <b><m>MIDI_note</m> <m>velocity</m> <m>MIDI_channel</m></b>,
				and then  plays them as MIDI (it contains a <o>noteout</o> inside it), unless the <m>noteout</m> attribute is
				unset. <br />
				The output <m>MIDI_note</m> is not in midicents, but in MIDI values (60 = middle C), the output <m>velocity</m> is the MIDI
				velocity (0 to 127, 0 being note-off), and the output <m>MIDI_channel</m> is of course the MIDI channel.
				For each note, a note-on and a note-off list is properly output. <br />
				The input expected llll must be formatted in the playout syntax (it is such by default if you link
				the playout of <o>bach.roll</o> or <o>bach.score</o> to the first <o>bach.ezmidiplay</o> inlet). <br /> <br />
				For <o>bach.roll</o>, the playout syntax is used whenever the information about a note or chord is sent through the playout (either at playtime
				or at offline play, or selection dump).
				The playout syntax is a slight variation of the standard chord gathered syntax. Two different cases apply, according to the <m>playmode</m>
				attribute value. If the <m>playmode</m> is set to Chordwise, the information about each chord is output in the form <br />
				<b>chord <m>voice_number</m> <m>MIDI_channel</m> (<m>onset</m> <m>NOTE1</m> <m>NOTE2</m> <m>NOTE3</m> <m>chord_flag</m>) </b> <br />
				where each <b><m>NOTE</m></b> is the gathered syntax of the note (see below).
				If the <m>playmode</m> is set to Notewise, information about each note is output as if the note were the only note in the chord, i.e. in the form <br />
				<b>note <m>voice_number</m> <m>MIDI_channel</m> (<m>onset</m> <m>NOTE</m> <m>chord_flag</m>) </b> <br />
				where <b><m>NOTE</m></b> is the note gathered syntax.
				The <m>MIDI_channels</m> is the one associated with the voice to which the note or chord belongs. The <m>onset</m> is in milliseconds,
				The <m>chord_flag</m> is a bitfield summing values of 1 (if chord is locked), 2 (if chord is muted), 4 (if chord is solo). <br />
				The playout syntax also concerns markers: they are output in the form: <b>marker <m>NAME_OR_NAMES</m> <m>onset_ms</m> <m>role</m> <m>optional:content</m></b>
				where the <m>NAME_OR_NAMES</m> is either a single atom (if the marker has a single name) or a wrapped plain llll containing the names, and the <m>optional:content</m>
				is only output if the marker role requires it.
				<br /> <br />
				In <o>bach.roll</o>, one can assign a role for each marker, so that they can represent elements such as
				time signatures, tempi, barline, measure divisions. Time signature markers and tempi markers
				also require a "content", i.e. an llll specifying the time signature or the tempo.
				When adding a marker via the <m>addmarker</m> message, the role can be specified as third parameter,
				and the content as fourth parameter. Alternatively, roles and content can be set via the marker inspector.
				Roles can be: <br />
				<m>Time Signature</m>: set by the symbol "timesig", it represents a time signature, and expects the time signature llll as content.
				For instance, a message to add such a marker could be <b>addmarker 0 foo timesig (4 4)</b>.<br />
				<m>Tempo</m>: set by the symbol "tempo", it represents a time signature, and expects the tempo llll as content (tempo figure and tempo
				value). For instance, a message to add such a marker could be <b>addmarker 0 foo tempo (1/8 50)</b>, meaning
				that the tempo is 1/8 = 50.<br />
				<m>Measure Barlines</m>: set by the symbol "barline", it represents a barline, and expects no content.
				For instance, a message to add such a marker could be <b>addmarker 0 foo barline</b>. <br />
				<m>Measure Division</m>: set by the symbol "division", it represents a measure division, and expects no content.
				For instance, a message to add such a marker could be <b>addmarker 0 foo division</b>. <br />
				<m>Measure Subdivision</m>: set by the symbol "subdivision", it represents a measure subdivision, and expects no content.
				For instance, a message to add such a marker could be <b>addmarker 0 foo subdivision</b>. <br />
				All these marker can be parsed by bach.quantize in order to automatically retrieve the measureinfo of the
				entire bach.roll.
				<br /> <br />
				For <o>bach.roll</o>, the gathered syntax for any note is, in its simplest form <b>(<m>pitch_cents</m> <m>duration</m> <m>velocity</m> <m>note_flag</m>)</b>
				where <m>pitch_cents</m> is the pitch of the note in MIDI cents, the <m>duration</m> is measured in milliseconds, the <m>velocity</m>
				is a value from 1 to 127 corresponding to the note dynamic, and
				the <m>note_flag</m> is an optional bitfield summing values of 1 (if note is locked), 2 (if note is muted), 4 (if note is solo). <br />
				In its most general form, each note can have different specifications and attributes, defining
				graphics, pitch breakpoints, slots, names.
				Each of these specifications is done in the form <b>(<m>specification_name</m> <m>SPECIFICATION CONTENT</m>)</b>, and must be put after the <m>velocity</m>
				and before the <m>note_flag</m>. The order in which the specifications are listed is, on the other hand, irrelevant. For instance, a note definition might have the form
				<b>(7300. 136. 127 (graphic 7400 -1/2) (slots (1 (0. 0. 0.) (0.294118 81.138889 0.) (0.294118 38.805556 0.) (1. 0. 0.))) (name pippo) 0 )</b>
				<br /> <br />
				Instead of MIDIcents (or cents), one can also instert pitches.
				The syntax for the single note must be an unique symbol (no spaces) with:
				<b><m>notename</m>-<m>optional:accidental</m>-<m>octave_number</m></b>.
				Dashes are only set in order to separate parts of the symbol, but must not be included in the symbol. <br /> <br />
				Names are in anglo-saxon syntax ("C", "D", "E"...), and are case insentitive. Middle C is C5.
				They and should be immediately followed by the possible accidentals and the
				octave number, without any space (e.g. <b>D#4</b>). <br />
				Accidentals are: <b>#</b> (sharp), <b>b</b> (flat), <b>x</b> (double sharp), <b>q</b> (quartertone sharp), <b>d</b> (quartertone flat),
				<b>^</b> (eighth-tone sharp), <b>v</b> (eighth-tone flat)
				One can also extend the accidental by setting a rational specification followed by a <b>t</b>. For instance <b>C5+1/16t</b> is
				middle C, 1/16 tone up.
				<br /> <br />
				The <m>graphic</m> specification informs about the enharmonicity status of a note.
				It is given by an llll in the form <b>(<m>graphic</m> <m>displayed_midicents_ignoring_accidental</m> <m>displayed_accidental</m>)</b>,
				where <m>displayed_midicents_ignoring_accidental</m> are the cents of the diatonic displayed note (ignoring any accidental that it might have),
				and <m>displayed_accidental</m> is the displayed accidental in rational form (sharp corresponding to 1/2, flat to -1/2, quarterflat to -1/4 and so on).
				For instance, a Db just above the middle C would have a graphic specification of <b>(graphics 6200 -1/2)</b>.
				<br /> <br />
				The <m>breakpoint</m> specification informs about possible pitch breakpoints that a note duration line has. This is useful to represent glissandi.
				It is given by an llll in the form <b>(<m>breakpoints</m> <m>BPT1</m> <m>BPT2</m> <m>BPT3</m>...)</b>,
				where each <m>BPT</m> is an llll in the form <b>(<m>relative_x_position</m> <m>delta_midicents</m> <m>slope</m>)</b>, where
				<m>relative_x_position</m> is a double precision number from 0 to 1 representing the point where the breakpoint is, 0 corresponding to
				the notehead and 1 corresponding to the note tail; <m>delta_midicents</m> is the pitch difference (in midicents) between the breakpoint pitch and the base note pitch;
				<m>slope</m> is a value from -1 to 1 corresponding to the curvature of the segment of duration line preceding the breakpoint (this implies that the slope of the first breakpoint
				is always ignored), as for Max <o>curve</o> object (thus 0 being linear). <br />
				Two breakpoints are always present: the first breakpoint corresponds always to (0 0 0), and can never
				be different than this; the last breakpoint corresponds always to the note tail, and must always be in the form <b>(1 <m>delta_midicents</m> <m>slope</m>)</b>.
				If all breakpoints are trivial (thus if there are just two breakpoints: notehead and tail, and the notetail has <m>delta_midicents</m> = 0), the breakpoint
				specification is never given as output. For instance, a note making a glissando upwards and then downwards of 200cents, linear while ascending and exponential in the descent,
				will have the breakpoint specification of the form <b>(breakpoints (0 0 0) (0.5 200 0) (1 0 0.5))</b>. <br />
				If the <m>breakpointshavevelocity</m> attribute is set to 1, pitch breakpoints also have velocities, thus the complete <m>BPT</m> specification is in the form
				(<m>relative_x_position</m> <m>delta_midicents</m> <m>slope</m> <m>velocity</m>),
				where <m>velocity</m> is a number from 1 to 127 corresponding to the pitch breakpoint dynamic. If different breapoints have different dynamics, the behavior of
				the velocity between them is considered to be interpolatory, for instance by abstractions like <o>bach.dl2line</o> or <o>bach.dl2curve</o>.
				<br /> <br />
				The <m>slots</m> specification informs about the content of each one (or a subset) of the slots of a note.
				It is given by an llll in the form <b>(slots <m>SLOT1</m> <m>SLOT2</m>...)</b>,
				where each one of the <m>SLOT</m> is an llll containing the information about one slot, in the form
				<b>(<m>slot_number</m> <m>SLOT_CONTENT</m>)</b>. <br />
				The slot content syntax depends on the slot type. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>function</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>POINT1</m> <m>POINT2</m> <m>POINT3</m>...</b> where each
				<m>POINT</m> is in turn in the form <b>(<m>x</m> <m>y</m> <m>slope</m>)</b>, where the first two elements are the coordinates of the point, and the last one is
				a slope parameter, from -1 to 1, corresponding to the curvature of the segment preceding the point. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>int</m> or <m>float</m> the content must be in the simplest form: <b><m>number</m></b>. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>intlist</m> or <m>floatlist</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>number1</m> <m>number2</m>...</b>. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>text</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>text_as_an_unique_symbol</m></b>. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>llll</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>WRAPPED_LLLL</m></b>, equivalent to <b>(<m>LLLL</m>)</b>.  <br />
				- For slot of type <m>filelist</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>filepath1</m> <m>filepath2</m> <m>filepath3</m>... <m>active_file_index</m></b>,
				where <m>active_file_index</m> is the index of the file which will appear as clicked (active). <br />
				- For slot of type <m>spat</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>SPATPOINT1</m> <m>SPATPOINT2</m> <m>SPATPOINT3</m>...</b> where each
				<m>SPATPOINT</m> is in turn in the form <b>(<m>t</m> <m>radius</m> <m>angle</m> <m>interpolation_type</m>)</b>,
				where the first element is the time position (by default, if the domain is temporal, this is between 0 and 1), then comes the radius
				(distance of the sound from the listener) and the angle which the sound makes with respect to a reference vertical direction.
				Last parameter is an interpolation type, which is 0 (default) for circular spatialization and 1 for linear spatialization. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>color</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>red</m> <m>green</m> <m>blue</m> <m>alpha</m></b>, where
				the parameters are the components of the RGBA color representation (from 0. to 1.).  <br />
				- For slot of type <m>3dfunction</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>POINT1</m> <m>POINT2</m> <m>POINT3</m>...</b> where each
				<m>POINT</m> is in turn in the form <b>(<m>x</m> <m>y</m> <m>z</m> <m>slope</m>)</b>, where the first three elements are the coordinates of the point, and the last one is
				a slope parameter, from -1 to 1, corresponding to the curvature of the segment preceding the point. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>filter</m>, when you need to input content you can use the syntax:
				<b><m>filtertype</m> <m>cutoff_frequency_Hz</m> <m>gain_dB</m> <m>Q_or_slope</m></b>, where <m>filtertype</m> is one of the following symbols:
				<m>lowpass</m>, <m>highpass</m>, <m>bandpass</m>, <m>bandstop</m>, <m>peaknotch</m>, <m>lowshelf</m>, <m>highshelf</m>, <m>allpass</m>.
				You can equivalently use for input the syntax
				<b><m>a0</m> <m>a0</m> <m>a2</m> <m>b1</m> <m>b2</m></b>, where the parameters are the coefficients of a biquad filter, as for <o>biquad~</o>.
				Finally, when data is output, the syntax is always a combination of the two:
				<b><m>a0</m> <m>a0</m> <m>a2</m> <m>b1</m> <m>b2</m> (<m>filtertype</m> <m>cutoff_frequency_Hz</m> <m>gain_dB</m> <m>Q_or_slope</m>)</b>. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>dynfilter</m> the content must be in the form: <b>(<m>t1</m> <m>FILTER1</m>) (<m>t2</m> <m>FILTER2</m>) (<m>t3</m> <m>FILTER3</m>)...</b>, where
				each <m>FILTER</m> is in the form defined for slot of type <m>filter</m>, just above. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>articulations</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>art1</m> <m>art2</m>...</b>, i.e. a sequence of
				articulations introduced as symbols.
				The list of the are standard available articulations as symbols is: "staccato" or "stacc", "staccatissimo" or "staccmo",
				"fermata" or "ferm", "portato" or "por", "accent" or "acc", "accentstaccato" or "accstacc", "accentportato" or "accport",
				"portatostaccato" or "portstacc", "martellato" or "mart", "martellatostaccato" or "martstacc", "lefthandpizzicato" or "lhpiz",
				"trill" or "tr", "gruppetto" or "grupp", "upmordent" or "umord", "downmordent" or "dmord", "doublemordent" or "mmord",
				"upbowing" or "ubow", "downbowing" or "dbow", "tremolo3" or "trem3" (for the tremolo with three slashes), "tremolo2" or "trem2"
				(for the tremolo with two slashes), "tremolo1" or "trem1" (for the tremolo with a single slash).
				Notice that the default bach font has all the articulations glyphs; however, not all the other supported fonts do,
				in particular Boulez doesn't have a certain number of the previous articulations among its glyphs.
				If you don't see an articulation as you wish
				(e.g. tremoli with Boulez), it might be because the font doesn't have the proper character, so try to use another font.
				Articulation symbols can also be retrieved by hovering on the corresponding element in the slot window. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>notehead</m> the content must a single notehead symbol.
				The list of the standard available noteheads as symbols is: "default", "doublewhole", "whole", "white", "black", "diamond", "cross", "plus",
				"none", "accent", "blacksquare", "whitesquare", "square" "blacktriangle", "whitetriangle", "triangle", "blackrhombus", "whiterhombus", "rhombus".
				In <o>bach.score</o>, the "square", "triangle" and "rhombus" notehead are black or white depending on the note duration; in <o>bach.roll</o> only
				the black flavour is used.
				As for articulations, not all fonts support all symbols.
				Notehead symbols can also be retrieved by hovering on the corresponding element in the slot window. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>togglematrix</m>, <m>intmatrix</m> or <m>floatmatrix</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>WRAPPED_MATRIX_AS_LLLL</m></b>,
				equivalent to <b>(<m>ROW1</m> <m>ROW2</m>...)</b>, where each row is a wrapped llll.
				In the bach environment, a matrix is just a llll having depth two, whose first-level sublllls are the rows of the matrix.
				For instance the matrix <b>(1 0 0) (0 1 0) (0 0 1)</b> is the 3 by 3 identity matrix. A "good" matrix is supposed to be well formed,
				i.e. all its rows must have the same length. A matrix is square if the length of the rows (which is the number of columns) is the same
				as the number of rows.
				<br /> <br />
				The <m>name</m> specification informs us about a possible name (or possibles names) of a notation item.
				It is simply given by an llll in the form <b>(name <m>NAME_OR_LLLL_OF_NAMES</m>)</b>,
				where <m>NAME_OR_LLLL_OF_NAMES</m> is either a single of symbols or integer, or an llll corresponding to the name(s) of the notation item.
				For instance, an item named as "john george" will correspond to the llll <b>(name john george)</b>.
				An item named "(high 1) (low 2)" will correspond to the llll <b>(name (high 1) (low 2))</b>.
				If an element has no names, the <m>name</m> specification is never given as output.
				<br /> <br />
				For <o>bach.score</o>, the playout syntax is used whenever the information about a note or chord is sent through the playout (either at playtime
				or at offline play, or selection dump).
				The playout syntax is a slight variation of the standard chord gathered syntax. Two different cases apply, according to the <m>playmode</m>
				attribute value. If the <m>playmode</m> is set to Chordwise, the information about each chord is output in the form <br />
				<b>chord <m>voice_number</m> <m>MIDI_channel</m> (<m>symbolic_duration</m> <m>duration_ms</m> <m>symbolic_onset_in_measure</m>
				<m>onset_from_score_beginning_in_ms</m> <m>NOTE1</m> <m>NOTE2</m> <m>NOTE3</m> <m>chord_flag</m>) </b> <br />
				where each <b><m>NOTE</m></b> is the gathered syntax of the note.
				If <m>playrest</m> is set to 1, and the chord is a rest, the router symbol is <b>rest</b> instead of chord. <br />
				If the <m>playmode</m> is set to Notewise, information about each note is output as if the note were the only note in the chord, i.e. in the form <br />
				<b>note <m>voice_number</m> <m>MIDI_channel</m> (<m>symbolic_duration</m> <m>duration_ms</m> <m>symbolic_onset_in_measure</m>
				<m>onset_from_score_beginning_in_ms</m> <m>NOTE</m> <m>note_flag</m>) </b> <br />
				where <m>NOTE</m> is the note gathered syntax. <br />
				If <m>playrest</m> is set to 1, and the chord is a rest, the router symbol is <b>rest</b> instead of chord, and there is no <m>NOTE</m> llll. <br />
				In case the played note or chord is just a grace chord, the <m>symbolic_duration</m> becomes an llll in the form <b>(g <m>grace_symbolic_duration</m>)</b>.
				The <m>MIDI_channels</m> is the one associated with the voice to which the note or chord belongs. The <m>onset</m> is in milliseconds,
				The <m>chord_flag</m> is a bitfield summing values of 1 (if chord is locked), 2 (if chord is muted), 4 (if chord is solo). <br />
				The playout syntax also concerns markers: they are output in the form: <b>marker <m>NAME_OR_NAMES</m> <m>ONSET</m> none</b>
				where the <m>NAME_OR_NAMES</m> is either a single atom (if the marker has a single name) or a wrapped llll containing the names.
				The last <b>none</b> symbol is the marker role, currently unsupported in <o>bach.score</o>. The <m>ONSET</m> can either be a single
				floating point value, representing the onset in milliseconds (if the marker is attached to the milliseconds position), or an llll representing
				the onset timepoint (if the marker is attached to the position inside the measure). <br />
				The playout syntax also concerns tempi: they are output in the form <b>tempo <m>voice_number</m> <m>tempo</m> <m>TEMPO_LLLL</m></b>,
				where <m>tempo</m> is the floating point tempo referred to the quarter note, and
				<m>TEMPO_LLLL</m> is in the form <b>(<m>tempo_figure</m> <m>tempo_value</m> <m>tempo_sym_onset</m> <m>interpolation_to_next?</m>)</b>.
				If the tempo starts an accelerando/rallentando (i.e. interpolation is set to 1), then the <m>tempo</m> element is substituted by the llll
				<b>(<m>tempo</m> <m>next_tempo</m> <m>interp_duration_ms</m>)</b>.  <br />
				The playout syntax also concerns measures: if <m>playmeasures</m> is 1, at the beginning of each measure (for each voice), an llll is output
				in the form <b>measure <m>voice_number</m> <m>measure_number</m> <m>MEASUREINFO_LLLL</m></b>.
				If a tempo and/or a chord lie at the beginning of a measure, the order of output for the elements is: measure, tempo, chord (or notes). <br />
				For all the previously exposed cases, if the <m>playoutfullpath</m> attribute is set to 1, the <m>voice_number</m> is substituted by
				an llll determining the address of the element (see the <m>playoutfullpath</m> attribute for more information. <br /> <br />
				A timepoint represents a given instant inside <o>bach.score</o>, as a measure-attached position.
				It identifies such point according to a measure, a position inside such measure,
				and possibly a voice (in case tempi and time signatures are not synchronous for all voices).
				Differently from absolute millisecond positions,
				timepoints are represented by lllls, in one of the following syntaxes: <br />
				- <b>(<m>measure_number</m>)</b>: represents the point is at the beginning of the measure identified by the introduced measure number, in the first voice.
				For instance, <b>(4)</b> represents the point at the very beginning of measure 4, voice 1. <br />
				- <b>(<m>measure_number</m> <m>sym_onset_in_measure</m>)</b>: represents the point inside the measure identified by the introduced measure number (in the first voice),
				but not necessarily at the beginning, rather at the generic position in measure identified by the symbolic onset <m>sym_onset_in_measure</m>.
				For instance, <b>(4 1/4)</b> represents the point at measure 4, voice 1, after 1/4 from the beginning of the measure. <br />
				- <b>(<m>voice_number</m> <m>measure_number</m> <m>sym_onset_in_measure</m>)</b>: represents the point inside the measure identified by the introduced measure number,
				in the voice identified, by the introduced voice number, at the generic position in measure identified by the symbolic onset <m>sym_onset_in_measure</m>.
				For instance, <b>(2 4 1/4)</b> represents the point at measure 4, voice 2, after 1/4 from the beginning of the measure. Specifying voice numbers explicitly is especially
				important if voices don't have the same tempi or time signatures.
				<br />
				A timepoint can also  be specified via a <b>(<m>float_measure_number</m>)</b>, representing the point in a floating
				point position between two measures (referred to the first voice). For instance, <b>(4.2)</b> represents the point at the 20% of measure 4, voice 1.
				Furthermore, the <m>sym_onset_in_measure</m> can be replaced by a float between 0 and 1 to represent a point between the beginning (0) and the end
				of the measure (1); for instance <b>(1 4 0.2)</b> represents the point after 20% of measure 4, voice 1.
				<br />
				If the measure number is replaced by the <b>any</b> symbol, then the following rational is interpreted as a global symbolic onset inside the score.
				For instance, <b>(any 27/4)</b> represents the point at 27/4 after the beginning of the score, referred to the measureinfo of voice 1;
				<b>(3 any 27/4)</b> does the same for voice 3.
				<br /> <br />
				For <o>bach.score</o>, the gathered syntax for any note is, in its simplest form <b>(<m>pitch_cents</m> <m>velocity</m> <m>tie?</m> <m>note_flag</m>)</b>
				where <m>pitch_cents</m> is the pitch of the note in MIDI cents, the <m>velocity</m>
				is a value from 1 to 127 corresponding to the note dynamic, the <m>tie?</m> value is 1 only if the note starts a tie and 0 otherwise, and
				the <m>note_flag</m> is an optional bitfield summing values of 1 (if note is locked), 2 (if note is muted), 4 (if note is solo). <br />
				In its most general form, each note can have different specifications and attributes, defining one of the possible extras:
				graphics, pitch breakpoints, slots, names, articulations.
				Each of these specifications is done in the form <b>(<m>specification_name</m> <m>SPECIFICATION CONTENT</m>)</b>, and must be put after the <m>tie?</m>
				and before the <m>note_flag</m>. The order in which the specifications are listed is, on the other hand, unimportant. For instance, a note definition might have the form
				<b>(7000. 127 1 (graphic 6900 1/2) (slots (1 (0. 112.5 0.) (1. 0. 0.))) (articulation stacc) (name foo) 0)</b>.
				<br /> <br />
				The <m>graphic</m> specification informs about the enharmonicity status of a note.
				It is given by an llll in the form <b>(<m>graphic</m> <m>displayed_midicents_ignoring_accidental</m> <m>displayed_accidental</m>)</b>,
				where <m>displayed_midicents_ignoring_accidental</m> are the cents of the diatonic displayed note (ignoring any accidental that it might have),
				and <m>displayed_accidental</m> is the displayed accidental in rational form (sharp corresponding to 1/2, flat to -1/2, quarterflat to -1/4 and so on).
				For instance, a Db just above the middle C would have a graphic specification of <b>(graphics 6200 -1/2)</b>.
				<br /> <br />
				The <m>breakpoint</m> specification informs about possible pitch breakpoints that a note duration line has. This is useful to represent glissandi.
				It is given by an llll in the form <b>(<m>breakpoints</m> <m>BPT1</m> <m>BPT2</m> <m>BPT3</m>...)</b>,
				where each <m>BPT</m> is an llll in the form <b>(<m>relative_x_position</m> <m>delta_midicents</m> <m>slope</m>)</b>, where
				<m>relative_x_position</m> is a double precision number from 0 to 1 representing the point where the breakpoint is, 0 corresponding to
				the notehead and 1 corresponding to the note tail; <m>delta_midicents</m> is the pitch difference (in midicents) between the breakpoint pitch and the base note pitch;
				<m>slope</m> is a value from -1 to 1 corresponding to the curvature of the segment of duration line preceding the breakpoint (this implies that the slope of the first breakpoint
				is always ignored), as for Max <o>curve</o> object (thus 0 being linear). <br />
				Two breakpoints are always present: the first breakpoint corresponds always to (0 0 0), and can never
				be different than this; the last breakpoint corresponds always to the note tail, and must always be in the form <b>(1 <m>delta_midicents</m> <m>slope</m>)</b>.
				If all breakpoints are trivial (thus if there are just two breakpoints: notehead and tail, and the notetail has <m>delta_midicents</m> = 0), the breakpoint
				specification is never given as output. For instance, a note making a glissando upwards and then downwards of 200cents, linear while ascending and exponential in the descent,
				will have the breakpoint specification of the form <b>(breakpoints (0 0 0) (0.5 200 0) (1 0 0.5))</b>. <br />
				If the <m>breakpointshavevelocity</m> attribute is set to 1, pitch breakpoints also have velocities, thus the complete <m>BPT</m> specification is in the form
				(<m>relative_x_position</m> <m>delta_midicents</m> <m>slope</m> <m>velocity</m>),
				where <m>velocity</m> is a number from 1 to 127 corresponding to the pitch breakpoint dynamic. If different breapoints have different dynamics, the behavior of
				the velocity between them is considered to be interpolatory, for instance by abstractions like <o>bach.dl2line</o> or <o>bach.dl2curve</o>.
				<br /> <br />
				The <m>slots</m> specification informs about the content of each one (or a subset) of the slots of a note.
				It is given by an llll in the form <b>(slots <m>SLOT1</m> <m>SLOT2</m>...)</b>,
				where each one of the <m>SLOT</m> is an llll containing the information about one slot, in the form
				<b>(<m>slot_number</m> <m>SLOT_CONTENT</m>)</b>. <br />
				The slot content syntax depends on the slot type. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>function</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>POINT1</m> <m>POINT2</m> <m>POINT3</m>...</b> where each
				<m>POINT</m> is in turn in the form <b>(<m>x</m> <m>y</m> <m>slope</m>)</b>, where the first two elements are the coordinates of the point, and the last one is
				a slope parameter, from -1 to 1, corresponding to the curvature of the segment preceding the point. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>int</m> or <m>float</m> the content must be in the simplest form: <b><m>number</m></b>. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>intlist</m> or <m>floatlist</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>number1</m> <m>number2</m>...</b>. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>text</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>text_as_an_unique_symbol</m></b>. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>llll</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>WRAPPED_LLLL</m></b>, equivalent to <b>(<m>LLLL</m>)</b>.  <br />
				- For slot of type <m>filelist</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>filepath1</m> <m>filepath2</m> <m>filepath3</m>... <m>active_file_index</m></b>,
				where <m>active_file_index</m> is the index of the file which will appear as clicked (active). <br />
				- For slot of type <m>spat</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>SPATPOINT1</m> <m>SPATPOINT2</m> <m>SPATPOINT3</m>...</b> where each
				<m>SPATPOINT</m> is in turn in the form <b>(<m>t</m> <m>radius</m> <m>angle</m> <m>interpolation_type</m>)</b>,
				where the first element is the time position (by default, if the domain is temporal, this is between 0 and 1), then comes the radius
				(distance of the sound from the listener) and the angle which the sound makes with respect to a reference vertical direction.
				Last parameter is an interpolation type, which is 0 (default) for circular spatialization and 1 for linear spatialization. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>color</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>red</m> <m>green</m> <m>blue</m> <m>alpha</m></b>, where
				the parameters are the components of the RGBA color representation (from 0. to 1.).  <br />
				- For slot of type <m>3dfunction</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>POINT1</m> <m>POINT2</m> <m>POINT3</m>...</b> where each
				<m>POINT</m> is in turn in the form <b>(<m>x</m> <m>y</m> <m>z</m> <m>slope</m>)</b>, where the first three elements are the coordinates of the point, and the last one is
				a slope parameter, from -1 to 1, corresponding to the curvature of the segment preceding the point. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>filter</m>, when you need to input content you can use the syntax:
				<b><m>filtertype</m> <m>cutoff_frequency_Hz</m> <m>gain_dB</m> <m>Q_or_slope</m></b>, where <m>filtertype</m> is one of the following symbols:
				<m>lowpass</m>, <m>highpass</m>, <m>bandpass</m>, <m>bandstop</m>, <m>peaknotch</m>, <m>lowshelf</m>, <m>highshelf</m>, <m>allpass</m>.
				You can equivalently use for input the syntax
				<b><m>a0</m> <m>a0</m> <m>a2</m> <m>b1</m> <m>b2</m></b>, where the parameters are the coefficients of a biquad filter, as for <o>biquad~</o>.
				Finally, when data is output, the syntax is always a combination of the two:
				<b><m>a0</m> <m>a0</m> <m>a2</m> <m>b1</m> <m>b2</m> (<m>filtertype</m> <m>cutoff_frequency_Hz</m> <m>gain_dB</m> <m>Q_or_slope</m>)</b>. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>dynfilter</m> the content must be in the form: <b>(<m>t1</m> <m>FILTER1</m>) (<m>t2</m> <m>FILTER2</m>) (<m>t3</m> <m>FILTER3</m>)...</b>, where
				each <m>FILTER</m> is in the form defined for slot of type <m>filter</m>, just above. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>articulations</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>art1</m> <m>art2</m>...</b>, i.e. a sequence of
				articulations introduced as symbols.
				The list of the are standard available articulations as symbols is: "staccato" or "stacc", "staccatissimo" or "staccmo",
				"fermata" or "ferm", "portato" or "por", "accent" or "acc", "accentstaccato" or "accstacc", "accentportato" or "accport",
				"portatostaccato" or "portstacc", "martellato" or "mart", "martellatostaccato" or "martstacc", "lefthandpizzicato" or "lhpiz",
				"trill" or "tr", "gruppetto" or "grupp", "upmordent" or "umord", "downmordent" or "dmord", "doublemordent" or "mmord",
				"upbowing" or "ubow", "downbowing" or "dbow", "tremolo3" or "trem3" (for the tremolo with three slashes), "tremolo2" or "trem2"
				(for the tremolo with two slashes), "tremolo1" or "trem1" (for the tremolo with a single slash).
				Notice that the default bach font has all the articulations glyphs; however, not all the other supported fonts do,
				in particular Boulez doesn't have a certain number of the previous articulations among its glyphs.
				If you don't see an articulation as you wish
				(e.g. tremoli with Boulez), it might be because the font doesn't have the proper character, so try to use another font.
				Articulation symbols can also be retrieved by hovering on the corresponding element in the slot window. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>notehead</m> the content must a single notehead symbol.
				The list of the standard available noteheads as symbols is: "default", "doublewhole", "whole", "white", "black", "diamond", "cross", "plus",
				"none", "accent", "blacksquare", "whitesquare", "square" "blacktriangle", "whitetriangle", "triangle", "blackrhombus", "whiterhombus", "rhombus".
				In <o>bach.score</o>, the "square", "triangle" and "rhombus" notehead are black or white depending on the note duration; in <o>bach.roll</o> only
				the black flavour is used.
				As for articulations, not all fonts support all symbols.
				Notehead symbols can also be retrieved by hovering on the corresponding element in the slot window. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>togglematrix</m>, <m>intmatrix</m> or <m>floatmatrix</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>WRAPPED_MATRIX_AS_LLLL</m></b>,
				equivalent to <b>(<m>ROW1</m> <m>ROW2</m>...)</b>, where each row is a wrapped llll.
				In the bach environment, a matrix is just a llll having depth two, whose first-level sublllls are the rows of the matrix.
				For instance the matrix <b>(1 0 0) (0 1 0) (0 0 1)</b> is the 3 by 3 identity matrix. A "good" matrix is supposed to be well formed,
				i.e. all its rows must have the same length. A matrix is square if the length of the rows (which is the number of columns) is the same
				as the number of rows.
				<br /> <br />
				The <m>name</m> specification informs us about a possible name (or possibles names) of a notation item.
				It is simply given by an llll in the form <b>(name <m>NAME_OR_LLLL_OF_NAMES</m>)</b>,
				where <m>NAME_OR_LLLL_OF_NAMES</m> is either a single of symbols or integer, or an llll corresponding to the name(s) of the notation item.
				For instance, an item named as "john george" will correspond to the llll <b>(name john george)</b>.
				An item named "(high 1) (low 2)" will correspond to the llll <b>(name (high 1) (low 2))</b>.
				If an element has no names, the <m>name</m> specification is never given as output.
				<br /> <br />
				The <m>articulation</m> specification informs us about an articulation assigned either to a chord or to a note.
				It is simply given by an llll in the form <b>(articulation <m>ARTICULATION_OR_LIST_OF_ARTICULATIONS</m>)</b>,
				where <m>ARTICULATION_OR_LIST_OF_ARTICULATIONS</m> is a list of symbols idenfitying articulations to be added to the notation item.
				The symbols of the list are allowed to be the following ones: "staccato" or "stacc", "staccatissimo" or "staccmo",
				"fermata" or "ferm", "portato" or "por", "accent" or "acc", "accentstaccato" or "accstacc", "accentportato" or "accport",
				"portatostaccato" or "portstacc", "martellato" or "mart", "martellatostaccato" or "martstacc", "lefthandpizzicato" or "lhpiz",
				"trill" or "tr", "gruppetto" or "grupp", "upmordent" or "umord", "downmordent" or "dmord", "doublemordent" or "mmord",
				"upbowing" or "ubow", "downbowing" or "dbow", "tremolo" or "trem" (for the tremolo with three slashes), "tremolo2" or "trem2"
				(for the tremolo with two slashes), "tremolo1" or "trem1" (for the tremolo with a single slash), "gruppetto" or "grupp". <br />
				The default bach font has all the articulations glyphs; however, not all the other supported fonts do, especially Boulez doesn't have
				a certain number of the previous articulations among its glyphs. If you don't see an articulation as you wish
				(e.g. tremoli with Boulez), it might be because the font doesn't have the proper character, so try to use another font.
				<br /> <br />
				Measureinfo is the information about time signature and tempo, plus some other optional specifications concerning the measure itself.
				This can be a single <b><m>TIME_SIGNATURE</m> <m>TEMPO</m></b> valid for all voices and all measures, or a llll containing for each measure and each voice
				an llll in the form <b>(<m>TIME_SIGNATURE</m> <m>TEMPO_OR_LIST_OF_TEMPI</m> <m>SPECIFICATION1</m> <m>SPECIFICATION2</m>...)</b>.
				All elements except for the <m>TIME_SIGNATURE</m> are optional. <br /> <br />
				The <m>TIME_SIGNATURE</m> is an llll containing the measure time signature, in one of the following forms: <br />
				- <b>(<m>numerator</m> <m>denominator</m>)</b> for standard time signatures. For instance, <b>(4 4)</b> corresponds to a 4/4 time signature. <br />
				- <b>((<m>numerator1</m> <m>numerator2</m> <m>numerator3</m>...) <m>denominator</m>)</b> for time
				signatures where the numerator is a sum of numbers.For instance <b>((3 2 3) 8)</b>
				corresponds to a (3+2+3)/8 time signature. <br /> <br />
				The <m>TEMPO_OR_LIST_OF_TEMPI</m> represent in its simplest form, a single tempo. <br />
				A tempo, defined for a measure of a <o>bach.score</o> has one of the following syntaxes: <br />
				- <b>(<m>tempo_value</m>)</b> will assign a quarter tempo at the beginning of the measure. For instance <b>(60)</b> will set a 1/4 = 60 tempo. <br />
				- <b>(<m>tempo_figure</m> <m>tempo_value</m>)</b> will assign the tempo value to the specified symbolic unit (at the beginning of the measure).
				The <m>tempo_figure</m> is indeed the tempo symbolic unit: for instance <b>(3/8 40)</b> will set a tempo of a dotted quarter = 40.<br />
				- <b>(<m>tempo_figure</m> <m>tempo_value</m> <m>tempo_sym_onset</m>)</b> will assign the tempo value to the specified symbolic unit and will put the
				tempo at the point inside the measure specified by the <m>tempo_sym_onset</m>. For instance <b>(3/8 40 1/4)</b> will set a tempo of a dotted quarter = 40
				but not at the beginning of the measure, rather after 1/4 from the beginning.<br />
				- <b>(<m>tempo_figure</m> <m>tempo_value</m> <m>tempo_sym_onset</m> <m>interpolation_to_next?</m>)</b> will do exactly as the previous case
				but if <m>interpolation_to_next?</m> is non-zero it will also toggle the interpolation from this tempo to the following one,
				yielding an accelerando or rallentando (depending if the next tempo is faster or slower). For instance <b>(3/8 40 1/4 1)</b>
				will set a tempo of a dotted quarter = 40, after 1/4 from the beginning, and will toggle the tempo interpolation to next tempo.<br />
				If more than one tempo need to be assigned to a given measure, one needs to use the general syntax for <m>TEMPO_OR_LIST_OF_TEMPI</m>, which is
				<b>(<m>TEMPO1</m> <m>TEMPO2</m> <m>TEMPO3</m>...)</b>, where each tempo must be in one the forms explained above. As an example, consider
				<b>((60) (1/4 70 1/16) (1/8 60 1/8 1) (1/8 80 3/8))</b>, where four tempi have been defined. The order of tempi is irrelevant,
				only their onset is accounted for. <br />
				Also, one might add an integer number at the beginning of each measure llll to indicate that the given measureinfo reference is valid for a
				certain number of measures, such as <b>(<m>how_many_measures</m> <m>TIME_SIGNATURE</m> <m>TEMPO_OR_LIST_OF_TEMPI</m> <m>SPECIFICATION1</m> <m>SPECIFICATION2</m>...)</b>.
				For instance <b>(5 (4 4) ((80) (1/4 160 1/2)))</b> creates 5 measures of 4/4, each one starting with quarter = 80, and then each one accelerating
				until 1/4 = 160 exactly at half of the measure. For instance
				<b> (((4 4) (1/8 60)) ((2 4) (1/4 50 1/4 1)) (4 (4 4)) (nil (180)))</b> means that we start a bar 1 in 4/4 and octave note = 60, then we
				pass at 2/4 and quarter = 50 after 1/4 of measure 2, and at that moment, an accelerando starts. The accelerando lasts during 4 4/4-measures,
				and then ends at the following measure on a new tempo of quarter = 180. <br /> <br />
				Each <m>SPECIFICATION</m> is an optional llll representing a given measure parameter, in the form <b>(<m>parameter_name</m> <m>parameter_value</m>)</b>.
				The <m>parameter_name</m> is a symbol identifying the parameter. The complete list of parameters symbols and their corresponding
				values is the following one: <br />
				- <b>width</b>: assigns a fixed width to a measure. It expects as value a fixed width in pixels that the measure will have (referred to the default
				vertical and horizontal zoom of 100%, and modified accordingly to those). Assigning a <m>width</m> parameter will also lock the measure barline,
				so that the width will remain the same, no matter how many chords and notes the measure does and will contain. Use the "auto" symbol
				instead of the fixed width to revert to the automatic measure width assignment (depending on the measure content). <br />
				- <b>widthfactor</b>: assigns a local factor for the spacing. It expects as value a multiplier factor, which will be applied to the whole measure
				spacing, and which will compress (for values less than 1) or expand (for values
				greater than 1) the width of the measure and the spacing of its chords accordingly. In this case, the measure barline is not locked, only the
				width factor is changed. <br />
				- <b>barline</b>: assigns a specific ending barline to a given measure. It expects a specific letter, representing the barline type. This letter
				can be one of the following ones: 'a' = automatic barline (defaul), 'n' = normal barline, 'd' = dashed barline, 'p' = dotted barline (p = "points"),
				't' = double barline (t = "two"), 's' = solid barline, 'f' = final barline, 'h' = hidden barline. <br />.
				- <b>shownumber</b>: deals with measure numbers. If an "off" symbol is given as value, it means that the measure number of the current measure will
				not be displayed. If a specific number is given, it will be assigned as a forced measure number to be displayed, for instance <b>(shownumber -4)</b> will
				show -4 as measure number (also see the attribute <m>measurenumberoffset</m>). If an "auto" symbol is given, it will show the measure's automatically
				assigned measure number (default). <br />
				- <b>boxes</b>: assign custom beaming boxes. It expects custom beaming boxes for the measure, as a plain list of rational numbers.
				Custom boxing allows you to handle beam grouping inside the measure differently than beat-wise.
				Each number of the expected list is the symbolic width of each beaming box inside the measure.
				If the given boxes don't fill the whole measure, the last one is padded. For instance, in a 4/4 measure,
				<b>(boxes 1/8)</b> will simply use eight 1/8-wide boxes to beam elements inside the measure, instead of the default 1/4 wide ones (beats).
				This is equivalent to <b>(boxes 1/8 1/8 1/8 1/8 1/8 1/8 1/8 1/8)</b>.
				Analogously, <b>(boxes 1/2 1/8 1/4 1/8)</b> is a more exotic boxing for the same time signature. <br />
				As a final example, (((4 4) (60) (widthfactor 0.5) (barline h) (shownumber off))) for a given measure sets a 4/4 time signature, a quarter = 60 tempo,
				compresses the measure by a factor of two, hides its final barline and its number.
				<br /> <br />
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="stop">
			<arglist />
			<digest>
				Stop all playing notes
			</digest>
			<description>
				The word <m>stop</m> stops all the currently playing notes.
			</description>
		</method>
	</methodlist>

	<!--ATTRIBUTES-->
	<attributelist>
		<attribute name="dataout" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1">
			<digest>
				Data Output Format
			</digest>
			<description>
				If this attribute is set to 0, nothing is output from the object's first outlet.
				If it is set to 1, the MIDI data is output in the form <b><m>MIDI note</m> <m>velocity</m> <m>MIDI channel</m></b>.
				If it is set to 2, the MIDI note is substituted by the bach MIDIcents, and the MIDI channel is the original channel
				(discarding possible changes due to microtonality).
			</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="label" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="Data Output Format" />
				<attribute name="paint" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1" value="1" />
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="text" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="durstretch" get="1" set="1" type="float" size="1">
			<digest>
				Duration Stretch Factor
			</digest>
			<description>
				Sets a factor to stretch each single duration. Defaults to 1.
			</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="label" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="Duration Stretch Factor" />
				<attribute name="paint" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1" value="1" />
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="text" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="maxpitchbend" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1">
			<digest>
				Maximum Pitch Bend
			</digest>
			<description>
				Since microtonal handling uses channels pitch-bending, if you build your own MIDI
				instrument, your maximum pitch bend could be different from General MIDI default one
				(2 semitones = 200 cents, up or down). You can thus specify via this attribute a maximum pitch bend
				in cents, so that it is accounted for when creating the multi-channel microtonal instruments
				(see the <m>int</m> method to know more).
			</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="label" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="Maximum Pitch Bend" />
				<attribute name="paint" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1" value="1" />
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="text" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="noteout" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1">
			<digest>
				Play MIDI notes
			</digest>
			<description>
				If this attribute is set to 0, no MIDI notes are played (the <o>noteout</o> object is unused),
				and the incoming playout lllls are just converted into MIDI triplets of <b><m>pitch</m> <m>velocity</m> <m>MIDI_channel</m></b> and output.
				If this attribute is set to 1 (default), MIDI notes are also played.
			</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="label" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="Play MIDI notes" />
				<attribute name="paint" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1" value="1" />
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="onoff" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="repeatmode" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1">
			<digest>
				Repeat Mode
			</digest>
			<description>
				As for <o>makenote</o>, sets the behavior when a note is retriggered. The modes are: <br />
				- Poly (0, default): There is no pre-specified behavior when you repeat a pitch before the note-off for that pitch has been sent.
				- Re-trigger (1): If a note is still playing when you retrigger it, the object will send a note-off (velocity 0) message to stop the
				first note and then send a new note-on message.
				- Stop Last (2): If a note is still playing when you retrigger it, the object will cancel the scheduled output of the first note -
				only the last played note will send note-off (velocity 0) message.
			</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="label" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="Repeat Mode" />
				<attribute name="paint" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1" value="1" />
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="enumindex" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
	</attributelist>

	<!--SEEALSO-->
	<seealsolist>
		<seealso name="bach.roll" />
		<seealso name="bach.score" />
		<seealso name="bach.playkeys" />
		<seealso name="makenote" />
		<seealso name="noteout" />
		<seealso name="02-Brother John" module="bach" type="tutorial" />
		<seealso name="06-The Gift Of Synthesis" module="bach" type="tutorial" />
	</seealsolist>

	<misc name = "Input">
		<entry name ="Inlet 1 (llll)">
			<description>
				The llll coming from <o>bach.roll</o> or <o>bach.score</o> playout.
				The expected llll must be formatted in the playout syntax (it is such by default if you link
				the playout of <o>bach.roll</o> or <o>bach.score</o> to the first <o>bach.ezmidiplay</o> inlet). <br /> <br />
				For <o>bach.roll</o>, the playout syntax is used whenever the information about a note or chord is sent through the playout (either at playtime
				or at offline play, or selection dump).
				The playout syntax is a slight variation of the standard chord gathered syntax. Two different cases apply, according to the <m>playmode</m>
				attribute value. If the <m>playmode</m> is set to Chordwise, the information about each chord is output in the form <br />
				<b>chord <m>voice_number</m> <m>MIDI_channel</m> (<m>onset</m> <m>NOTE1</m> <m>NOTE2</m> <m>NOTE3</m> <m>chord_flag</m>) </b> <br />
				where each <b><m>NOTE</m></b> is the gathered syntax of the note (see below).
				If the <m>playmode</m> is set to Notewise, information about each note is output as if the note were the only note in the chord, i.e. in the form <br />
				<b>note <m>voice_number</m> <m>MIDI_channel</m> (<m>onset</m> <m>NOTE</m> <m>chord_flag</m>) </b> <br />
				where <b><m>NOTE</m></b> is the note gathered syntax.
				The <m>MIDI_channels</m> is the one associated with the voice to which the note or chord belongs. The <m>onset</m> is in milliseconds,
				The <m>chord_flag</m> is a bitfield summing values of 1 (if chord is locked), 2 (if chord is muted), 4 (if chord is solo). <br />
				The playout syntax also concerns markers: they are output in the form: <b>marker <m>NAME_OR_NAMES</m> <m>onset_ms</m> <m>role</m> <m>optional:content</m></b>
				where the <m>NAME_OR_NAMES</m> is either a single atom (if the marker has a single name) or a wrapped plain llll containing the names, and the <m>optional:content</m>
				is only output if the marker role requires it.
				<br /> <br />
				In <o>bach.roll</o>, one can assign a role for each marker, so that they can represent elements such as
				time signatures, tempi, barline, measure divisions. Time signature markers and tempi markers
				also require a "content", i.e. an llll specifying the time signature or the tempo.
				When adding a marker via the <m>addmarker</m> message, the role can be specified as third parameter,
				and the content as fourth parameter. Alternatively, roles and content can be set via the marker inspector.
				Roles can be: <br />
				<m>Time Signature</m>: set by the symbol "timesig", it represents a time signature, and expects the time signature llll as content.
				For instance, a message to add such a marker could be <b>addmarker 0 foo timesig (4 4)</b>.<br />
				<m>Tempo</m>: set by the symbol "tempo", it represents a time signature, and expects the tempo llll as content (tempo figure and tempo
				value). For instance, a message to add such a marker could be <b>addmarker 0 foo tempo (1/8 50)</b>, meaning
				that the tempo is 1/8 = 50.<br />
				<m>Measure Barlines</m>: set by the symbol "barline", it represents a barline, and expects no content.
				For instance, a message to add such a marker could be <b>addmarker 0 foo barline</b>. <br />
				<m>Measure Division</m>: set by the symbol "division", it represents a measure division, and expects no content.
				For instance, a message to add such a marker could be <b>addmarker 0 foo division</b>. <br />
				<m>Measure Subdivision</m>: set by the symbol "subdivision", it represents a measure subdivision, and expects no content.
				For instance, a message to add such a marker could be <b>addmarker 0 foo subdivision</b>. <br />
				All these marker can be parsed by bach.quantize in order to automatically retrieve the measureinfo of the
				entire bach.roll.
				<br /> <br />
				For <o>bach.roll</o>, the gathered syntax for any note is, in its simplest form <b>(<m>pitch_cents</m> <m>duration</m> <m>velocity</m> <m>note_flag</m>)</b>
				where <m>pitch_cents</m> is the pitch of the note in MIDI cents, the <m>duration</m> is measured in milliseconds, the <m>velocity</m>
				is a value from 1 to 127 corresponding to the note dynamic, and
				the <m>note_flag</m> is an optional bitfield summing values of 1 (if note is locked), 2 (if note is muted), 4 (if note is solo). <br />
				In its most general form, each note can have different specifications and attributes, defining
				graphics, pitch breakpoints, slots, names.
				Each of these specifications is done in the form <b>(<m>specification_name</m> <m>SPECIFICATION CONTENT</m>)</b>, and must be put after the <m>velocity</m>
				and before the <m>note_flag</m>. The order in which the specifications are listed is, on the other hand, irrelevant. For instance, a note definition might have the form
				<b>(7300. 136. 127 (graphic 7400 -1/2) (slots (1 (0. 0. 0.) (0.294118 81.138889 0.) (0.294118 38.805556 0.) (1. 0. 0.))) (name pippo) 0 )</b>
				<br /> <br />
				Instead of MIDIcents (or cents), one can also instert pitches.
				The syntax for the single note must be an unique symbol (no spaces) with:
				<b><m>notename</m>-<m>optional:accidental</m>-<m>octave_number</m></b>.
				Dashes are only set in order to separate parts of the symbol, but must not be included in the symbol. <br /> <br />
				Names are in anglo-saxon syntax ("C", "D", "E"...), and are case insentitive. Middle C is C5.
				They and should be immediately followed by the possible accidentals and the
				octave number, without any space (e.g. <b>D#4</b>). <br />
				Accidentals are: <b>#</b> (sharp), <b>b</b> (flat), <b>x</b> (double sharp), <b>q</b> (quartertone sharp), <b>d</b> (quartertone flat),
				<b>^</b> (eighth-tone sharp), <b>v</b> (eighth-tone flat)
				One can also extend the accidental by setting a rational specification followed by a <b>t</b>. For instance <b>C5+1/16t</b> is
				middle C, 1/16 tone up.
				<br /> <br />
				The <m>graphic</m> specification informs about the enharmonicity status of a note.
				It is given by an llll in the form <b>(<m>graphic</m> <m>displayed_midicents_ignoring_accidental</m> <m>displayed_accidental</m>)</b>,
				where <m>displayed_midicents_ignoring_accidental</m> are the cents of the diatonic displayed note (ignoring any accidental that it might have),
				and <m>displayed_accidental</m> is the displayed accidental in rational form (sharp corresponding to 1/2, flat to -1/2, quarterflat to -1/4 and so on).
				For instance, a Db just above the middle C would have a graphic specification of <b>(graphics 6200 -1/2)</b>.
				<br /> <br />
				The <m>breakpoint</m> specification informs about possible pitch breakpoints that a note duration line has. This is useful to represent glissandi.
				It is given by an llll in the form <b>(<m>breakpoints</m> <m>BPT1</m> <m>BPT2</m> <m>BPT3</m>...)</b>,
				where each <m>BPT</m> is an llll in the form <b>(<m>relative_x_position</m> <m>delta_midicents</m> <m>slope</m>)</b>, where
				<m>relative_x_position</m> is a double precision number from 0 to 1 representing the point where the breakpoint is, 0 corresponding to
				the notehead and 1 corresponding to the note tail; <m>delta_midicents</m> is the pitch difference (in midicents) between the breakpoint pitch and the base note pitch;
				<m>slope</m> is a value from -1 to 1 corresponding to the curvature of the segment of duration line preceding the breakpoint (this implies that the slope of the first breakpoint
				is always ignored), as for Max <o>curve</o> object (thus 0 being linear). <br />
				Two breakpoints are always present: the first breakpoint corresponds always to (0 0 0), and can never
				be different than this; the last breakpoint corresponds always to the note tail, and must always be in the form <b>(1 <m>delta_midicents</m> <m>slope</m>)</b>.
				If all breakpoints are trivial (thus if there are just two breakpoints: notehead and tail, and the notetail has <m>delta_midicents</m> = 0), the breakpoint
				specification is never given as output. For instance, a note making a glissando upwards and then downwards of 200cents, linear while ascending and exponential in the descent,
				will have the breakpoint specification of the form <b>(breakpoints (0 0 0) (0.5 200 0) (1 0 0.5))</b>. <br />
				If the <m>breakpointshavevelocity</m> attribute is set to 1, pitch breakpoints also have velocities, thus the complete <m>BPT</m> specification is in the form
				(<m>relative_x_position</m> <m>delta_midicents</m> <m>slope</m> <m>velocity</m>),
				where <m>velocity</m> is a number from 1 to 127 corresponding to the pitch breakpoint dynamic. If different breapoints have different dynamics, the behavior of
				the velocity between them is considered to be interpolatory, for instance by abstractions like <o>bach.dl2line</o> or <o>bach.dl2curve</o>.
				<br /> <br />
				The <m>slots</m> specification informs about the content of each one (or a subset) of the slots of a note.
				It is given by an llll in the form <b>(slots <m>SLOT1</m> <m>SLOT2</m>...)</b>,
				where each one of the <m>SLOT</m> is an llll containing the information about one slot, in the form
				<b>(<m>slot_number</m> <m>SLOT_CONTENT</m>)</b>. <br />
				The slot content syntax depends on the slot type. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>function</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>POINT1</m> <m>POINT2</m> <m>POINT3</m>...</b> where each
				<m>POINT</m> is in turn in the form <b>(<m>x</m> <m>y</m> <m>slope</m>)</b>, where the first two elements are the coordinates of the point, and the last one is
				a slope parameter, from -1 to 1, corresponding to the curvature of the segment preceding the point. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>int</m> or <m>float</m> the content must be in the simplest form: <b><m>number</m></b>. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>intlist</m> or <m>floatlist</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>number1</m> <m>number2</m>...</b>. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>text</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>text_as_an_unique_symbol</m></b>. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>llll</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>WRAPPED_LLLL</m></b>, equivalent to <b>(<m>LLLL</m>)</b>.  <br />
				- For slot of type <m>filelist</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>filepath1</m> <m>filepath2</m> <m>filepath3</m>... <m>active_file_index</m></b>,
				where <m>active_file_index</m> is the index of the file which will appear as clicked (active). <br />
				- For slot of type <m>spat</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>SPATPOINT1</m> <m>SPATPOINT2</m> <m>SPATPOINT3</m>...</b> where each
				<m>SPATPOINT</m> is in turn in the form <b>(<m>t</m> <m>radius</m> <m>angle</m> <m>interpolation_type</m>)</b>,
				where the first element is the time position (by default, if the domain is temporal, this is between 0 and 1), then comes the radius
				(distance of the sound from the listener) and the angle which the sound makes with respect to a reference vertical direction.
				Last parameter is an interpolation type, which is 0 (default) for circular spatialization and 1 for linear spatialization. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>color</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>red</m> <m>green</m> <m>blue</m> <m>alpha</m></b>, where
				the parameters are the components of the RGBA color representation (from 0. to 1.).  <br />
				- For slot of type <m>3dfunction</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>POINT1</m> <m>POINT2</m> <m>POINT3</m>...</b> where each
				<m>POINT</m> is in turn in the form <b>(<m>x</m> <m>y</m> <m>z</m> <m>slope</m>)</b>, where the first three elements are the coordinates of the point, and the last one is
				a slope parameter, from -1 to 1, corresponding to the curvature of the segment preceding the point. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>filter</m>, when you need to input content you can use the syntax:
				<b><m>filtertype</m> <m>cutoff_frequency_Hz</m> <m>gain_dB</m> <m>Q_or_slope</m></b>, where <m>filtertype</m> is one of the following symbols:
				<m>lowpass</m>, <m>highpass</m>, <m>bandpass</m>, <m>bandstop</m>, <m>peaknotch</m>, <m>lowshelf</m>, <m>highshelf</m>, <m>allpass</m>.
				You can equivalently use for input the syntax
				<b><m>a0</m> <m>a0</m> <m>a2</m> <m>b1</m> <m>b2</m></b>, where the parameters are the coefficients of a biquad filter, as for <o>biquad~</o>.
				Finally, when data is output, the syntax is always a combination of the two:
				<b><m>a0</m> <m>a0</m> <m>a2</m> <m>b1</m> <m>b2</m> (<m>filtertype</m> <m>cutoff_frequency_Hz</m> <m>gain_dB</m> <m>Q_or_slope</m>)</b>. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>dynfilter</m> the content must be in the form: <b>(<m>t1</m> <m>FILTER1</m>) (<m>t2</m> <m>FILTER2</m>) (<m>t3</m> <m>FILTER3</m>)...</b>, where
				each <m>FILTER</m> is in the form defined for slot of type <m>filter</m>, just above. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>articulations</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>art1</m> <m>art2</m>...</b>, i.e. a sequence of
				articulations introduced as symbols.
				The list of the are standard available articulations as symbols is: "staccato" or "stacc", "staccatissimo" or "staccmo",
				"fermata" or "ferm", "portato" or "por", "accent" or "acc", "accentstaccato" or "accstacc", "accentportato" or "accport",
				"portatostaccato" or "portstacc", "martellato" or "mart", "martellatostaccato" or "martstacc", "lefthandpizzicato" or "lhpiz",
				"trill" or "tr", "gruppetto" or "grupp", "upmordent" or "umord", "downmordent" or "dmord", "doublemordent" or "mmord",
				"upbowing" or "ubow", "downbowing" or "dbow", "tremolo3" or "trem3" (for the tremolo with three slashes), "tremolo2" or "trem2"
				(for the tremolo with two slashes), "tremolo1" or "trem1" (for the tremolo with a single slash).
				Notice that the default bach font has all the articulations glyphs; however, not all the other supported fonts do,
				in particular Boulez doesn't have a certain number of the previous articulations among its glyphs.
				If you don't see an articulation as you wish
				(e.g. tremoli with Boulez), it might be because the font doesn't have the proper character, so try to use another font.
				Articulation symbols can also be retrieved by hovering on the corresponding element in the slot window. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>notehead</m> the content must a single notehead symbol.
				The list of the standard available noteheads as symbols is: "default", "doublewhole", "whole", "white", "black", "diamond", "cross", "plus",
				"none", "accent", "blacksquare", "whitesquare", "square" "blacktriangle", "whitetriangle", "triangle", "blackrhombus", "whiterhombus", "rhombus".
				In <o>bach.score</o>, the "square", "triangle" and "rhombus" notehead are black or white depending on the note duration; in <o>bach.roll</o> only
				the black flavour is used.
				As for articulations, not all fonts support all symbols.
				Notehead symbols can also be retrieved by hovering on the corresponding element in the slot window. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>togglematrix</m>, <m>intmatrix</m> or <m>floatmatrix</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>WRAPPED_MATRIX_AS_LLLL</m></b>,
				equivalent to <b>(<m>ROW1</m> <m>ROW2</m>...)</b>, where each row is a wrapped llll.
				In the bach environment, a matrix is just a llll having depth two, whose first-level sublllls are the rows of the matrix.
				For instance the matrix <b>(1 0 0) (0 1 0) (0 0 1)</b> is the 3 by 3 identity matrix. A "good" matrix is supposed to be well formed,
				i.e. all its rows must have the same length. A matrix is square if the length of the rows (which is the number of columns) is the same
				as the number of rows.
				<br /> <br />
				The <m>name</m> specification informs us about a possible name (or possibles names) of a notation item.
				It is simply given by an llll in the form <b>(name <m>NAME_OR_LLLL_OF_NAMES</m>)</b>,
				where <m>NAME_OR_LLLL_OF_NAMES</m> is either a single of symbols or integer, or an llll corresponding to the name(s) of the notation item.
				For instance, an item named as "john george" will correspond to the llll <b>(name john george)</b>.
				An item named "(high 1) (low 2)" will correspond to the llll <b>(name (high 1) (low 2))</b>.
				If an element has no names, the <m>name</m> specification is never given as output.
				<br /> <br />
				For <o>bach.score</o>, the playout syntax is used whenever the information about a note or chord is sent through the playout (either at playtime
				or at offline play, or selection dump).
				The playout syntax is a slight variation of the standard chord gathered syntax. Two different cases apply, according to the <m>playmode</m>
				attribute value. If the <m>playmode</m> is set to Chordwise, the information about each chord is output in the form <br />
				<b>chord <m>voice_number</m> <m>MIDI_channel</m> (<m>symbolic_duration</m> <m>duration_ms</m> <m>symbolic_onset_in_measure</m>
				<m>onset_from_score_beginning_in_ms</m> <m>NOTE1</m> <m>NOTE2</m> <m>NOTE3</m> <m>chord_flag</m>) </b> <br />
				where each <b><m>NOTE</m></b> is the gathered syntax of the note.
				If <m>playrest</m> is set to 1, and the chord is a rest, the router symbol is <b>rest</b> instead of chord. <br />
				If the <m>playmode</m> is set to Notewise, information about each note is output as if the note were the only note in the chord, i.e. in the form <br />
				<b>note <m>voice_number</m> <m>MIDI_channel</m> (<m>symbolic_duration</m> <m>duration_ms</m> <m>symbolic_onset_in_measure</m>
				<m>onset_from_score_beginning_in_ms</m> <m>NOTE</m> <m>note_flag</m>) </b> <br />
				where <m>NOTE</m> is the note gathered syntax. <br />
				If <m>playrest</m> is set to 1, and the chord is a rest, the router symbol is <b>rest</b> instead of chord, and there is no <m>NOTE</m> llll. <br />
				In case the played note or chord is just a grace chord, the <m>symbolic_duration</m> becomes an llll in the form <b>(g <m>grace_symbolic_duration</m>)</b>.
				The <m>MIDI_channels</m> is the one associated with the voice to which the note or chord belongs. The <m>onset</m> is in milliseconds,
				The <m>chord_flag</m> is a bitfield summing values of 1 (if chord is locked), 2 (if chord is muted), 4 (if chord is solo). <br />
				The playout syntax also concerns markers: they are output in the form: <b>marker <m>NAME_OR_NAMES</m> <m>ONSET</m> none</b>
				where the <m>NAME_OR_NAMES</m> is either a single atom (if the marker has a single name) or a wrapped llll containing the names.
				The last <b>none</b> symbol is the marker role, currently unsupported in <o>bach.score</o>. The <m>ONSET</m> can either be a single
				floating point value, representing the onset in milliseconds (if the marker is attached to the milliseconds position), or an llll representing
				the onset timepoint (if the marker is attached to the position inside the measure). <br />
				The playout syntax also concerns tempi: they are output in the form <b>tempo <m>voice_number</m> <m>tempo</m> <m>TEMPO_LLLL</m></b>,
				where <m>tempo</m> is the floating point tempo referred to the quarter note, and
				<m>TEMPO_LLLL</m> is in the form <b>(<m>tempo_figure</m> <m>tempo_value</m> <m>tempo_sym_onset</m> <m>interpolation_to_next?</m>)</b>.
				If the tempo starts an accelerando/rallentando (i.e. interpolation is set to 1), then the <m>tempo</m> element is substituted by the llll
				<b>(<m>tempo</m> <m>next_tempo</m> <m>interp_duration_ms</m>)</b>.  <br />
				The playout syntax also concerns measures: if <m>playmeasures</m> is 1, at the beginning of each measure (for each voice), an llll is output
				in the form <b>measure <m>voice_number</m> <m>measure_number</m> <m>MEASUREINFO_LLLL</m></b>.
				If a tempo and/or a chord lie at the beginning of a measure, the order of output for the elements is: measure, tempo, chord (or notes). <br />
				For all the previously exposed cases, if the <m>playoutfullpath</m> attribute is set to 1, the <m>voice_number</m> is substituted by
				an llll determining the address of the element (see the <m>playoutfullpath</m> attribute for more information. <br /> <br />
				A timepoint represents a given instant inside <o>bach.score</o>, as a measure-attached position.
				It identifies such point according to a measure, a position inside such measure,
				and possibly a voice (in case tempi and time signatures are not synchronous for all voices).
				Differently from absolute millisecond positions,
				timepoints are represented by lllls, in one of the following syntaxes: <br />
				- <b>(<m>measure_number</m>)</b>: represents the point is at the beginning of the measure identified by the introduced measure number, in the first voice.
				For instance, <b>(4)</b> represents the point at the very beginning of measure 4, voice 1. <br />
				- <b>(<m>measure_number</m> <m>sym_onset_in_measure</m>)</b>: represents the point inside the measure identified by the introduced measure number (in the first voice),
				but not necessarily at the beginning, rather at the generic position in measure identified by the symbolic onset <m>sym_onset_in_measure</m>.
				For instance, <b>(4 1/4)</b> represents the point at measure 4, voice 1, after 1/4 from the beginning of the measure. <br />
				- <b>(<m>voice_number</m> <m>measure_number</m> <m>sym_onset_in_measure</m>)</b>: represents the point inside the measure identified by the introduced measure number,
				in the voice identified, by the introduced voice number, at the generic position in measure identified by the symbolic onset <m>sym_onset_in_measure</m>.
				For instance, <b>(2 4 1/4)</b> represents the point at measure 4, voice 2, after 1/4 from the beginning of the measure. Specifying voice numbers explicitly is especially
				important if voices don't have the same tempi or time signatures.
				<br />
				A timepoint can also  be specified via a <b>(<m>float_measure_number</m>)</b>, representing the point in a floating
				point position between two measures (referred to the first voice). For instance, <b>(4.2)</b> represents the point at the 20% of measure 4, voice 1.
				Furthermore, the <m>sym_onset_in_measure</m> can be replaced by a float between 0 and 1 to represent a point between the beginning (0) and the end
				of the measure (1); for instance <b>(1 4 0.2)</b> represents the point after 20% of measure 4, voice 1.
				<br />
				If the measure number is replaced by the <b>any</b> symbol, then the following rational is interpreted as a global symbolic onset inside the score.
				For instance, <b>(any 27/4)</b> represents the point at 27/4 after the beginning of the score, referred to the measureinfo of voice 1;
				<b>(3 any 27/4)</b> does the same for voice 3.
				<br /> <br />
				For <o>bach.score</o>, the gathered syntax for any note is, in its simplest form <b>(<m>pitch_cents</m> <m>velocity</m> <m>tie?</m> <m>note_flag</m>)</b>
				where <m>pitch_cents</m> is the pitch of the note in MIDI cents, the <m>velocity</m>
				is a value from 1 to 127 corresponding to the note dynamic, the <m>tie?</m> value is 1 only if the note starts a tie and 0 otherwise, and
				the <m>note_flag</m> is an optional bitfield summing values of 1 (if note is locked), 2 (if note is muted), 4 (if note is solo). <br />
				In its most general form, each note can have different specifications and attributes, defining one of the possible extras:
				graphics, pitch breakpoints, slots, names, articulations.
				Each of these specifications is done in the form <b>(<m>specification_name</m> <m>SPECIFICATION CONTENT</m>)</b>, and must be put after the <m>tie?</m>
				and before the <m>note_flag</m>. The order in which the specifications are listed is, on the other hand, unimportant. For instance, a note definition might have the form
				<b>(7000. 127 1 (graphic 6900 1/2) (slots (1 (0. 112.5 0.) (1. 0. 0.))) (articulation stacc) (name foo) 0)</b>.
				<br /> <br />
				The <m>graphic</m> specification informs about the enharmonicity status of a note.
				It is given by an llll in the form <b>(<m>graphic</m> <m>displayed_midicents_ignoring_accidental</m> <m>displayed_accidental</m>)</b>,
				where <m>displayed_midicents_ignoring_accidental</m> are the cents of the diatonic displayed note (ignoring any accidental that it might have),
				and <m>displayed_accidental</m> is the displayed accidental in rational form (sharp corresponding to 1/2, flat to -1/2, quarterflat to -1/4 and so on).
				For instance, a Db just above the middle C would have a graphic specification of <b>(graphics 6200 -1/2)</b>.
				<br /> <br />
				The <m>breakpoint</m> specification informs about possible pitch breakpoints that a note duration line has. This is useful to represent glissandi.
				It is given by an llll in the form <b>(<m>breakpoints</m> <m>BPT1</m> <m>BPT2</m> <m>BPT3</m>...)</b>,
				where each <m>BPT</m> is an llll in the form <b>(<m>relative_x_position</m> <m>delta_midicents</m> <m>slope</m>)</b>, where
				<m>relative_x_position</m> is a double precision number from 0 to 1 representing the point where the breakpoint is, 0 corresponding to
				the notehead and 1 corresponding to the note tail; <m>delta_midicents</m> is the pitch difference (in midicents) between the breakpoint pitch and the base note pitch;
				<m>slope</m> is a value from -1 to 1 corresponding to the curvature of the segment of duration line preceding the breakpoint (this implies that the slope of the first breakpoint
				is always ignored), as for Max <o>curve</o> object (thus 0 being linear). <br />
				Two breakpoints are always present: the first breakpoint corresponds always to (0 0 0), and can never
				be different than this; the last breakpoint corresponds always to the note tail, and must always be in the form <b>(1 <m>delta_midicents</m> <m>slope</m>)</b>.
				If all breakpoints are trivial (thus if there are just two breakpoints: notehead and tail, and the notetail has <m>delta_midicents</m> = 0), the breakpoint
				specification is never given as output. For instance, a note making a glissando upwards and then downwards of 200cents, linear while ascending and exponential in the descent,
				will have the breakpoint specification of the form <b>(breakpoints (0 0 0) (0.5 200 0) (1 0 0.5))</b>. <br />
				If the <m>breakpointshavevelocity</m> attribute is set to 1, pitch breakpoints also have velocities, thus the complete <m>BPT</m> specification is in the form
				(<m>relative_x_position</m> <m>delta_midicents</m> <m>slope</m> <m>velocity</m>),
				where <m>velocity</m> is a number from 1 to 127 corresponding to the pitch breakpoint dynamic. If different breapoints have different dynamics, the behavior of
				the velocity between them is considered to be interpolatory, for instance by abstractions like <o>bach.dl2line</o> or <o>bach.dl2curve</o>.
				<br /> <br />
				The <m>slots</m> specification informs about the content of each one (or a subset) of the slots of a note.
				It is given by an llll in the form <b>(slots <m>SLOT1</m> <m>SLOT2</m>...)</b>,
				where each one of the <m>SLOT</m> is an llll containing the information about one slot, in the form
				<b>(<m>slot_number</m> <m>SLOT_CONTENT</m>)</b>. <br />
				The slot content syntax depends on the slot type. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>function</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>POINT1</m> <m>POINT2</m> <m>POINT3</m>...</b> where each
				<m>POINT</m> is in turn in the form <b>(<m>x</m> <m>y</m> <m>slope</m>)</b>, where the first two elements are the coordinates of the point, and the last one is
				a slope parameter, from -1 to 1, corresponding to the curvature of the segment preceding the point. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>int</m> or <m>float</m> the content must be in the simplest form: <b><m>number</m></b>. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>intlist</m> or <m>floatlist</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>number1</m> <m>number2</m>...</b>. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>text</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>text_as_an_unique_symbol</m></b>. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>llll</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>WRAPPED_LLLL</m></b>, equivalent to <b>(<m>LLLL</m>)</b>.  <br />
				- For slot of type <m>filelist</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>filepath1</m> <m>filepath2</m> <m>filepath3</m>... <m>active_file_index</m></b>,
				where <m>active_file_index</m> is the index of the file which will appear as clicked (active). <br />
				- For slot of type <m>spat</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>SPATPOINT1</m> <m>SPATPOINT2</m> <m>SPATPOINT3</m>...</b> where each
				<m>SPATPOINT</m> is in turn in the form <b>(<m>t</m> <m>radius</m> <m>angle</m> <m>interpolation_type</m>)</b>,
				where the first element is the time position (by default, if the domain is temporal, this is between 0 and 1), then comes the radius
				(distance of the sound from the listener) and the angle which the sound makes with respect to a reference vertical direction.
				Last parameter is an interpolation type, which is 0 (default) for circular spatialization and 1 for linear spatialization. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>color</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>red</m> <m>green</m> <m>blue</m> <m>alpha</m></b>, where
				the parameters are the components of the RGBA color representation (from 0. to 1.).  <br />
				- For slot of type <m>3dfunction</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>POINT1</m> <m>POINT2</m> <m>POINT3</m>...</b> where each
				<m>POINT</m> is in turn in the form <b>(<m>x</m> <m>y</m> <m>z</m> <m>slope</m>)</b>, where the first three elements are the coordinates of the point, and the last one is
				a slope parameter, from -1 to 1, corresponding to the curvature of the segment preceding the point. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>filter</m>, when you need to input content you can use the syntax:
				<b><m>filtertype</m> <m>cutoff_frequency_Hz</m> <m>gain_dB</m> <m>Q_or_slope</m></b>, where <m>filtertype</m> is one of the following symbols:
				<m>lowpass</m>, <m>highpass</m>, <m>bandpass</m>, <m>bandstop</m>, <m>peaknotch</m>, <m>lowshelf</m>, <m>highshelf</m>, <m>allpass</m>.
				You can equivalently use for input the syntax
				<b><m>a0</m> <m>a0</m> <m>a2</m> <m>b1</m> <m>b2</m></b>, where the parameters are the coefficients of a biquad filter, as for <o>biquad~</o>.
				Finally, when data is output, the syntax is always a combination of the two:
				<b><m>a0</m> <m>a0</m> <m>a2</m> <m>b1</m> <m>b2</m> (<m>filtertype</m> <m>cutoff_frequency_Hz</m> <m>gain_dB</m> <m>Q_or_slope</m>)</b>. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>dynfilter</m> the content must be in the form: <b>(<m>t1</m> <m>FILTER1</m>) (<m>t2</m> <m>FILTER2</m>) (<m>t3</m> <m>FILTER3</m>)...</b>, where
				each <m>FILTER</m> is in the form defined for slot of type <m>filter</m>, just above. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>articulations</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>art1</m> <m>art2</m>...</b>, i.e. a sequence of
				articulations introduced as symbols.
				The list of the are standard available articulations as symbols is: "staccato" or "stacc", "staccatissimo" or "staccmo",
				"fermata" or "ferm", "portato" or "por", "accent" or "acc", "accentstaccato" or "accstacc", "accentportato" or "accport",
				"portatostaccato" or "portstacc", "martellato" or "mart", "martellatostaccato" or "martstacc", "lefthandpizzicato" or "lhpiz",
				"trill" or "tr", "gruppetto" or "grupp", "upmordent" or "umord", "downmordent" or "dmord", "doublemordent" or "mmord",
				"upbowing" or "ubow", "downbowing" or "dbow", "tremolo3" or "trem3" (for the tremolo with three slashes), "tremolo2" or "trem2"
				(for the tremolo with two slashes), "tremolo1" or "trem1" (for the tremolo with a single slash).
				Notice that the default bach font has all the articulations glyphs; however, not all the other supported fonts do,
				in particular Boulez doesn't have a certain number of the previous articulations among its glyphs.
				If you don't see an articulation as you wish
				(e.g. tremoli with Boulez), it might be because the font doesn't have the proper character, so try to use another font.
				Articulation symbols can also be retrieved by hovering on the corresponding element in the slot window. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>notehead</m> the content must a single notehead symbol.
				The list of the standard available noteheads as symbols is: "default", "doublewhole", "whole", "white", "black", "diamond", "cross", "plus",
				"none", "accent", "blacksquare", "whitesquare", "square" "blacktriangle", "whitetriangle", "triangle", "blackrhombus", "whiterhombus", "rhombus".
				In <o>bach.score</o>, the "square", "triangle" and "rhombus" notehead are black or white depending on the note duration; in <o>bach.roll</o> only
				the black flavour is used.
				As for articulations, not all fonts support all symbols.
				Notehead symbols can also be retrieved by hovering on the corresponding element in the slot window. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>togglematrix</m>, <m>intmatrix</m> or <m>floatmatrix</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>WRAPPED_MATRIX_AS_LLLL</m></b>,
				equivalent to <b>(<m>ROW1</m> <m>ROW2</m>...)</b>, where each row is a wrapped llll.
				In the bach environment, a matrix is just a llll having depth two, whose first-level sublllls are the rows of the matrix.
				For instance the matrix <b>(1 0 0) (0 1 0) (0 0 1)</b> is the 3 by 3 identity matrix. A "good" matrix is supposed to be well formed,
				i.e. all its rows must have the same length. A matrix is square if the length of the rows (which is the number of columns) is the same
				as the number of rows.
				<br /> <br />
				The <m>name</m> specification informs us about a possible name (or possibles names) of a notation item.
				It is simply given by an llll in the form <b>(name <m>NAME_OR_LLLL_OF_NAMES</m>)</b>,
				where <m>NAME_OR_LLLL_OF_NAMES</m> is either a single of symbols or integer, or an llll corresponding to the name(s) of the notation item.
				For instance, an item named as "john george" will correspond to the llll <b>(name john george)</b>.
				An item named "(high 1) (low 2)" will correspond to the llll <b>(name (high 1) (low 2))</b>.
				If an element has no names, the <m>name</m> specification is never given as output.
				<br /> <br />
				The <m>articulation</m> specification informs us about an articulation assigned either to a chord or to a note.
				It is simply given by an llll in the form <b>(articulation <m>ARTICULATION_OR_LIST_OF_ARTICULATIONS</m>)</b>,
				where <m>ARTICULATION_OR_LIST_OF_ARTICULATIONS</m> is a list of symbols idenfitying articulations to be added to the notation item.
				The symbols of the list are allowed to be the following ones: "staccato" or "stacc", "staccatissimo" or "staccmo",
				"fermata" or "ferm", "portato" or "por", "accent" or "acc", "accentstaccato" or "accstacc", "accentportato" or "accport",
				"portatostaccato" or "portstacc", "martellato" or "mart", "martellatostaccato" or "martstacc", "lefthandpizzicato" or "lhpiz",
				"trill" or "tr", "gruppetto" or "grupp", "upmordent" or "umord", "downmordent" or "dmord", "doublemordent" or "mmord",
				"upbowing" or "ubow", "downbowing" or "dbow", "tremolo" or "trem" (for the tremolo with three slashes), "tremolo2" or "trem2"
				(for the tremolo with two slashes), "tremolo1" or "trem1" (for the tremolo with a single slash), "gruppetto" or "grupp". <br />
				The default bach font has all the articulations glyphs; however, not all the other supported fonts do, especially Boulez doesn't have
				a certain number of the previous articulations among its glyphs. If you don't see an articulation as you wish
				(e.g. tremoli with Boulez), it might be because the font doesn't have the proper character, so try to use another font.
				<br /> <br />
				Measureinfo is the information about time signature and tempo, plus some other optional specifications concerning the measure itself.
				This can be a single <b><m>TIME_SIGNATURE</m> <m>TEMPO</m></b> valid for all voices and all measures, or a llll containing for each measure and each voice
				an llll in the form <b>(<m>TIME_SIGNATURE</m> <m>TEMPO_OR_LIST_OF_TEMPI</m> <m>SPECIFICATION1</m> <m>SPECIFICATION2</m>...)</b>.
				All elements except for the <m>TIME_SIGNATURE</m> are optional. <br /> <br />
				The <m>TIME_SIGNATURE</m> is an llll containing the measure time signature, in one of the following forms: <br />
				- <b>(<m>numerator</m> <m>denominator</m>)</b> for standard time signatures. For instance, <b>(4 4)</b> corresponds to a 4/4 time signature. <br />
				- <b>((<m>numerator1</m> <m>numerator2</m> <m>numerator3</m>...) <m>denominator</m>)</b> for time
				signatures where the numerator is a sum of numbers.For instance <b>((3 2 3) 8)</b>
				corresponds to a (3+2+3)/8 time signature. <br /> <br />
				The <m>TEMPO_OR_LIST_OF_TEMPI</m> represent in its simplest form, a single tempo. <br />
				A tempo, defined for a measure of a <o>bach.score</o> has one of the following syntaxes: <br />
				- <b>(<m>tempo_value</m>)</b> will assign a quarter tempo at the beginning of the measure. For instance <b>(60)</b> will set a 1/4 = 60 tempo. <br />
				- <b>(<m>tempo_figure</m> <m>tempo_value</m>)</b> will assign the tempo value to the specified symbolic unit (at the beginning of the measure).
				The <m>tempo_figure</m> is indeed the tempo symbolic unit: for instance <b>(3/8 40)</b> will set a tempo of a dotted quarter = 40.<br />
				- <b>(<m>tempo_figure</m> <m>tempo_value</m> <m>tempo_sym_onset</m>)</b> will assign the tempo value to the specified symbolic unit and will put the
				tempo at the point inside the measure specified by the <m>tempo_sym_onset</m>. For instance <b>(3/8 40 1/4)</b> will set a tempo of a dotted quarter = 40
				but not at the beginning of the measure, rather after 1/4 from the beginning.<br />
				- <b>(<m>tempo_figure</m> <m>tempo_value</m> <m>tempo_sym_onset</m> <m>interpolation_to_next?</m>)</b> will do exactly as the previous case
				but if <m>interpolation_to_next?</m> is non-zero it will also toggle the interpolation from this tempo to the following one,
				yielding an accelerando or rallentando (depending if the next tempo is faster or slower). For instance <b>(3/8 40 1/4 1)</b>
				will set a tempo of a dotted quarter = 40, after 1/4 from the beginning, and will toggle the tempo interpolation to next tempo.<br />
				If more than one tempo need to be assigned to a given measure, one needs to use the general syntax for <m>TEMPO_OR_LIST_OF_TEMPI</m>, which is
				<b>(<m>TEMPO1</m> <m>TEMPO2</m> <m>TEMPO3</m>...)</b>, where each tempo must be in one the forms explained above. As an example, consider
				<b>((60) (1/4 70 1/16) (1/8 60 1/8 1) (1/8 80 3/8))</b>, where four tempi have been defined. The order of tempi is irrelevant,
				only their onset is accounted for. <br />
				Also, one might add an integer number at the beginning of each measure llll to indicate that the given measureinfo reference is valid for a
				certain number of measures, such as <b>(<m>how_many_measures</m> <m>TIME_SIGNATURE</m> <m>TEMPO_OR_LIST_OF_TEMPI</m> <m>SPECIFICATION1</m> <m>SPECIFICATION2</m>...)</b>.
				For instance <b>(5 (4 4) ((80) (1/4 160 1/2)))</b> creates 5 measures of 4/4, each one starting with quarter = 80, and then each one accelerating
				until 1/4 = 160 exactly at half of the measure. For instance
				<b> (((4 4) (1/8 60)) ((2 4) (1/4 50 1/4 1)) (4 (4 4)) (nil (180)))</b> means that we start a bar 1 in 4/4 and octave note = 60, then we
				pass at 2/4 and quarter = 50 after 1/4 of measure 2, and at that moment, an accelerando starts. The accelerando lasts during 4 4/4-measures,
				and then ends at the following measure on a new tempo of quarter = 180. <br /> <br />
				Each <m>SPECIFICATION</m> is an optional llll representing a given measure parameter, in the form <b>(<m>parameter_name</m> <m>parameter_value</m>)</b>.
				The <m>parameter_name</m> is a symbol identifying the parameter. The complete list of parameters symbols and their corresponding
				values is the following one: <br />
				- <b>width</b>: assigns a fixed width to a measure. It expects as value a fixed width in pixels that the measure will have (referred to the default
				vertical and horizontal zoom of 100%, and modified accordingly to those). Assigning a <m>width</m> parameter will also lock the measure barline,
				so that the width will remain the same, no matter how many chords and notes the measure does and will contain. Use the "auto" symbol
				instead of the fixed width to revert to the automatic measure width assignment (depending on the measure content). <br />
				- <b>widthfactor</b>: assigns a local factor for the spacing. It expects as value a multiplier factor, which will be applied to the whole measure
				spacing, and which will compress (for values less than 1) or expand (for values
				greater than 1) the width of the measure and the spacing of its chords accordingly. In this case, the measure barline is not locked, only the
				width factor is changed. <br />
				- <b>barline</b>: assigns a specific ending barline to a given measure. It expects a specific letter, representing the barline type. This letter
				can be one of the following ones: 'a' = automatic barline (defaul), 'n' = normal barline, 'd' = dashed barline, 'p' = dotted barline (p = "points"),
				't' = double barline (t = "two"), 's' = solid barline, 'f' = final barline, 'h' = hidden barline. <br />.
				- <b>shownumber</b>: deals with measure numbers. If an "off" symbol is given as value, it means that the measure number of the current measure will
				not be displayed. If a specific number is given, it will be assigned as a forced measure number to be displayed, for instance <b>(shownumber -4)</b> will
				show -4 as measure number (also see the attribute <m>measurenumberoffset</m>). If an "auto" symbol is given, it will show the measure's automatically
				assigned measure number (default). <br />
				- <b>boxes</b>: assign custom beaming boxes. It expects custom beaming boxes for the measure, as a plain list of rational numbers.
				Custom boxing allows you to handle beam grouping inside the measure differently than beat-wise.
				Each number of the expected list is the symbolic width of each beaming box inside the measure.
				If the given boxes don't fill the whole measure, the last one is padded. For instance, in a 4/4 measure,
				<b>(boxes 1/8)</b> will simply use eight 1/8-wide boxes to beam elements inside the measure, instead of the default 1/4 wide ones (beats).
				This is equivalent to <b>(boxes 1/8 1/8 1/8 1/8 1/8 1/8 1/8 1/8)</b>.
				Analogously, <b>(boxes 1/2 1/8 1/4 1/8)</b> is a more exotic boxing for the same time signature. <br />
				As a final example, (((4 4) (60) (widthfactor 0.5) (barline h) (shownumber off))) for a given measure sets a 4/4 time signature, a quarter = 60 tempo,
				compresses the measure by a factor of two, hides its final barline and its number.
				<br /> <br />
			</description>
		</entry>
		<entry name ="Inlet 2 (list)">
			<description>
				Messages to <o>noteout</o>.
				Send in the third inlet all the messages that you want to send directly to the <o>noteout</o>
				inside the abstraction, such as the MIDI port.
			</description>
		</entry>
	</misc>

	<misc name = "Output">
		<entry name ="Outlet 1 (list)">
			<description>
				The list containing MIDI triplets.
				Triplets of MIDI data in the form <b><m>MIDI_note</m> <m>velocity</m> <m>MIDI_channel</m></b>.
				where <m>MIDI_note</m> is not in midicents, but in MIDI values (60 = middle C), <m>velocity</m> is the MIDI
				velocity (0 to 127, 0 being note-off), and <m>MIDI_channel</m> is of course the MIDI channel.
				For each note, a note-on and a note-off list is properly sent.
			</description>
		</entry>
		<entry name ="Outlet 2 (int)">
			<description>
				Number of available channels.
				The number of channels which could actually be used by the user (ignoring the percussion 10th channel),
				the other ones being used to handle microtonality (see <m>int</m> method for more information).
			</description>
		</entry>
	</misc>

</c74object>