<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="./_c74_ref.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!--This file has been automatically generated by Doctor Max. DO NOT EDIT THIS FILE DIRECTLY.-->

<c74object name="bach.slot2line" module="bach" kind="patcher">

	<digest>
		Convert a function-slot content into messages for <o>line~</o>
	</digest>

	<description>
		Converts the llll content of a given slot,
		of type "function", into a list of messages for <o>line~</o>.
		Slopes of slot segments are ignored.
	</description>

	<!--METADATA-->
	<metadatalist>
		<metadata name="author">bachproject</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">bach</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">bach abstractions</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">bach notation</metadata>
	</metadatalist>

	<!--INLETS-->
	<inletlist>
		<inlet id="0" type="INLET_TYPE">
			<digest>
				The duration of the function in milliseconds
			</digest>
			<description>
			</description>
		</inlet>
		<inlet id="1" type="INLET_TYPE">
			<digest>
				The llll containing the function slot content
			</digest>
			<description>
			</description>
		</inlet>
		<inlet id="2" type="INLET_TYPE">
			<digest>
				The default value
			</digest>
			<description>
			</description>
		</inlet>
		<inlet id="3" type="INLET_TYPE">
			<digest>
				Lambda inlet
			</digest>
			<description>
				A lambda inlet is an inlet receiving the answer from a test or modification performed on elements sent out the lambda outlets. <br />
				In this case, the answer is expected to be a modification of the elements which had been sent out:
				the element output via the lambda outlet can be customly modified and then plugged in into this lambda inlet:
				such modification will be accounted for by the algorithm. <br />
				The lambda inlet also accepts the result in llll form, so you can sometimes avoid the explicit @out t. <br />
				It is important to know that the evaluation chain inside the lambda loop must be direct: you can't use objects such as <o>delay</o>,
				<o>pipe</o>, <o>defer</o>; nor store the value anywhere waiting for some other event to trigger it. Also see #lambda in the bach Help Center.
				<br /> <br />
			</description>
		</inlet>
	</inletlist>

	<!--OUTLETS-->
	<outletlist>
		<outlet id="0" type="INLET_TYPE">
			<digest>
				The messages for <o>line~</o>
			</digest>
			<description>
			</description>
		</outlet>
		<outlet id="1" type="INLET_TYPE">
			<digest>
				Lambda outlet
			</digest>
			<description>
				A lambda outlet is an outlet outputting an element on which some test or modification must be performed.
				The result of the test or modification is then expected in a lambda inlet. <br />
				In this case, the elements output from the lambda outlet may be customly modified, so that such modification will be taken into
				account by the algorithm. To modify each element, just use patching and then plug into the lambda inlet the
				modified version of the element. <br />
				It is important to know that the evaluation chain inside the lambda loop must be direct: you can't use objects such as <o>delay</o>,
				<o>pipe</o>, <o>defer</o>; nor store the value anywhere waiting for some other event to trigger it. Also see #lambda in the bach Help Center.
				<br /> <br />
			</description>
		</outlet>
	</outletlist>

	<!--ARGUMENTS-->
	<objarglist>
		<objarg name="default_value" optional="1" type="float">
			<digest>
				Default value
			</digest>
			<description>
				A floating point number given as argument sets a default value which will be
				sent to <o>line~</o> if no function is defined in the incoming slot (slot content is empty).
			</description>
		</objarg>
	</objarglist>

	<!--MESSAGES-->
	<methodlist>
		<method name="bang">
			<arglist />
			<digest>
				Output messages
			</digest>
			<description>
				Outputs messages for <o>line~</o>, based on the most recently received input data.
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="float">
			<arglist />
			<digest>
				Function depends on inlet
			</digest>
			<description>
				A floating point number in the first inlet is considered as the overall duration of the function,
				and will trigger the output of the conversion of the slot content into messages for <o>line~</o>,
				output from the first outlet. <br />
				A floating point number in the third inlet sets a default value which will be
				sent to <o>line~</o> if no function is defined in the incoming slot (slot content is empty). <br />
				A floating point number in the fourth inlet is the answer of a lambda loop, allowing to remap function amplitudes.
				This is handy, for instance, if you had a function slot representing amplitudes in decibels, and you need to convert
				them into linear amplitude representation in order to send them to <o>line~</o>.
				Indeed, fourth inlet is a lambda inlet. <br />
				A lambda inlet is an inlet receiving the answer from a test or modification performed on elements sent out the lambda outlets. <br />
				In this case, the answer is expected to be a modification of the elements which had been sent out:
				the element output via the lambda outlet can be customly modified and then plugged in into this lambda inlet:
				such modification will be accounted for by the algorithm. <br />
				The lambda inlet also accepts the result in llll form, so you can sometimes avoid the explicit @out t. <br />
				It is important to know that the evaluation chain inside the lambda loop must be direct: you can't use objects such as <o>delay</o>,
				<o>pipe</o>, <o>defer</o>; nor store the value anywhere waiting for some other event to trigger it. Also see #lambda in the bach Help Center.
				<br /> <br />
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="llll">
			<arglist />
			<digest>
				Set slot content
			</digest>
			<description>
				An llll in the second inlet is considered as the function slot content.
				Typically this is obtained from <o>bach.playkeys</o>'s slots outlets.
				See below for the precise syntax of the slot content (for <o>bach.slot2line</o> only
				syntax for function slots is relevant). <br />
				An llll in the fourth (lambda) inlet is considered as a floating point number in llll native form
				(see <m>float</m> message for more information).
				<br /> <br />
				The slot content syntax depends on the slot type. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>function</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>POINT1</m> <m>POINT2</m> <m>POINT3</m>...</b> where each
				<m>POINT</m> is in turn in the form <b>(<m>x</m> <m>y</m> <m>slope</m>)</b>, where the first two elements are the coordinates of the point, and the last one is
				a slope parameter, from -1 to 1, corresponding to the curvature of the segment preceding the point. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>int</m> or <m>float</m> the content must be in the simplest form: <b><m>number</m></b>. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>intlist</m> or <m>floatlist</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>number1</m> <m>number2</m>...</b>. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>text</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>text_as_an_unique_symbol</m></b>. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>llll</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>WRAPPED_LLLL</m></b>, equivalent to <b>(<m>LLLL</m>)</b>.  <br />
				- For slot of type <m>filelist</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>filepath1</m> <m>filepath2</m> <m>filepath3</m>... <m>active_file_index</m></b>,
				where <m>active_file_index</m> is the index of the file which will appear as clicked (active). <br />
				- For slot of type <m>spat</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>SPATPOINT1</m> <m>SPATPOINT2</m> <m>SPATPOINT3</m>...</b> where each
				<m>SPATPOINT</m> is in turn in the form <b>(<m>t</m> <m>radius</m> <m>angle</m> <m>interpolation_type</m>)</b>,
				where the first element is the time position (by default, if the domain is temporal, this is between 0 and 1), then comes the radius
				(distance of the sound from the listener) and the angle which the sound makes with respect to a reference vertical direction.
				Last parameter is an interpolation type, which is 0 (default) for circular spatialization and 1 for linear spatialization. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>color</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>red</m> <m>green</m> <m>blue</m> <m>alpha</m></b>, where
				the parameters are the components of the RGBA color representation (from 0. to 1.).  <br />
				- For slot of type <m>3dfunction</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>POINT1</m> <m>POINT2</m> <m>POINT3</m>...</b> where each
				<m>POINT</m> is in turn in the form <b>(<m>x</m> <m>y</m> <m>z</m> <m>slope</m>)</b>, where the first three elements are the coordinates of the point, and the last one is
				a slope parameter, from -1 to 1, corresponding to the curvature of the segment preceding the point. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>filter</m>, when you need to input content you can use the syntax:
				<b><m>filtertype</m> <m>cutoff_frequency_Hz</m> <m>gain_dB</m> <m>Q_or_slope</m></b>, where <m>filtertype</m> is one of the following symbols:
				<m>lowpass</m>, <m>highpass</m>, <m>bandpass</m>, <m>bandstop</m>, <m>peaknotch</m>, <m>lowshelf</m>, <m>highshelf</m>, <m>allpass</m>.
				You can equivalently use for input the syntax
				<b><m>a0</m> <m>a0</m> <m>a2</m> <m>b1</m> <m>b2</m></b>, where the parameters are the coefficients of a biquad filter, as for <o>biquad~</o>.
				Finally, when data is output, the syntax is always a combination of the two:
				<b><m>a0</m> <m>a0</m> <m>a2</m> <m>b1</m> <m>b2</m> (<m>filtertype</m> <m>cutoff_frequency_Hz</m> <m>gain_dB</m> <m>Q_or_slope</m>)</b>. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>dynfilter</m> the content must be in the form: <b>(<m>t1</m> <m>FILTER1</m>) (<m>t2</m> <m>FILTER2</m>) (<m>t3</m> <m>FILTER3</m>)...</b>, where
				each <m>FILTER</m> is in the form defined for slot of type <m>filter</m>, just above. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>articulations</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>art1</m> <m>art2</m>...</b>, i.e. a sequence of
				articulations introduced as symbols.
				The list of the are standard available articulations as symbols is: "staccato" or "stacc", "staccatissimo" or "staccmo",
				"fermata" or "ferm", "portato" or "por", "accent" or "acc", "accentstaccato" or "accstacc", "accentportato" or "accport",
				"portatostaccato" or "portstacc", "martellato" or "mart", "martellatostaccato" or "martstacc", "lefthandpizzicato" or "lhpiz",
				"trill" or "tr", "gruppetto" or "grupp", "upmordent" or "umord", "downmordent" or "dmord", "doublemordent" or "mmord",
				"upbowing" or "ubow", "downbowing" or "dbow", "tremolo3" or "trem3" (for the tremolo with three slashes), "tremolo2" or "trem2"
				(for the tremolo with two slashes), "tremolo1" or "trem1" (for the tremolo with a single slash).
				Notice that the default bach font has all the articulations glyphs; however, not all the other supported fonts do,
				in particular Boulez doesn't have a certain number of the previous articulations among its glyphs.
				If you don't see an articulation as you wish
				(e.g. tremoli with Boulez), it might be because the font doesn't have the proper character, so try to use another font.
				Articulation symbols can also be retrieved by hovering on the corresponding element in the slot window. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>notehead</m> the content must a single notehead symbol.
				The list of the standard available noteheads as symbols is: "default", "doublewhole", "whole", "white", "black", "diamond", "cross", "plus",
				"none", "accent", "blacksquare", "whitesquare", "square" "blacktriangle", "whitetriangle", "triangle", "blackrhombus", "whiterhombus", "rhombus".
				In <o>bach.score</o>, the "square", "triangle" and "rhombus" notehead are black or white depending on the note duration; in <o>bach.roll</o> only
				the black flavour is used.
				As for articulations, not all fonts support all symbols.
				Notehead symbols can also be retrieved by hovering on the corresponding element in the slot window. <br />
				- For slot of type <m>togglematrix</m>, <m>intmatrix</m> or <m>floatmatrix</m> the content must be in the form: <b><m>WRAPPED_MATRIX_AS_LLLL</m></b>,
				equivalent to <b>(<m>ROW1</m> <m>ROW2</m>...)</b>, where each row is a wrapped llll.
				In the bach environment, a matrix is just a llll having depth two, whose first-level sublllls are the rows of the matrix.
				For instance the matrix <b>(1 0 0) (0 1 0) (0 0 1)</b> is the 3 by 3 identity matrix. A "good" matrix is supposed to be well formed,
				i.e. all its rows must have the same length. A matrix is square if the length of the rows (which is the number of columns) is the same
				as the number of rows.
				<br /> <br />
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="milliseconds">
			<arglist />
			<digest>
				Convert Slot in Milliseconds Mode
			</digest>
			<description>
				A <m>milliseconds</m> message in the first inlet will consider
				the slot information coming from the second inlet as a slot in "Milliseconds"
				temporal mode (see <m>temporalmode</m> specification of the slotinfo),
				and will trigger the output of the conversion of the slot content into messages for <o>line~</o>,
				output from the first outlet. <br />
			</description>
		</method>
	</methodlist>

	<!--ATTRIBUTES-->
	<attributelist>
		<attribute name="out" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1">
			<digest>
				Outlet Types
			</digest>
			<description>
				The <m>out</m> attribute is a sequence of characters identifying the outlet types (one character for each llll outlet). Characters can be one of the following: <br />
				<m>n</m> (default): 'native' output: faster and more precise between bach objects, but unreadable by standard Max objects (an "bach.llll" message appears instead). <br />
				<m>t</m>: 'text' output: slower and limited in size, but readable by standard Max objects. A plain llll in text format is a generic Max message.
				To keep the representation invertible (i.e., to allow a bach object receiving a text-format llll to interpret it exactly as if it was native format,
				except for the size limitation), some specific kinds of symbols are preceded by a backtick: namely, symbols containing parens, or containing textual
				representations of numbers or pitches, or beginning with a backtick, plus the symbols "null" and "nil" (distinct from the reserved words
				"null" and "nil" representing the empty list and the empty sublist) are preceded by a backtick. Moreover, the symbols "int", "float" or "list"
				are preceded by a backtick only if they are the first element of an llll, to distinguish them from the corresponding reserved messages of Max. <br />
				<m>m</m>: 'max' output: mostly equivalent to the <t> specifier, but no symbol is backticket except "int", "float" and "list" at the beginning of an llll.
				It is important to notice that, differently from text-format lllls proper, Max-format lllls might not be invertible even if they do not reach the size
				limit for Max message. This means that a bach object receiving a Max-format llll output from another bach object might interpret it differently
				from the original, or in some cases might even reject it. <br />
				<m>x</m>: disabled output (nothing is output) <br />
				<m>p</m>: 'portal' output: only used by bach.portal to intercept the @out attribute specified while creating the abstraction (see bach.portal). <br />
				The native output is recommended, unless communication with standard Max messages is needed.
				Disabling unused outputs can be useful if extreme optimization of the patch is needed.
				<br /> <br />
			</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="category" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="Behavior" />
				<attribute name="label" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="Outlet Types" />
				<attribute name="paint" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1" value="1" />
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="text" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
	</attributelist>

	<!--SEEALSO-->
	<seealsolist>
		<seealso name="line~" />
		<seealso name="bach.slot2curve" />
		<seealso name="bach.roll" />
		<seealso name="bach.score" />
		<seealso name="bach.slot" />
	</seealsolist>

	<misc name = "Input">
		<entry name ="Inlet 1 (float)">
			<description>
				The duration of the function in milliseconds.
			</description>
		</entry>
		<entry name ="Inlet 2 (llll)">
			<description>
				The llll containing the function slot content.
			</description>
		</entry>
		<entry name ="Inlet 3 (float)">
			<description>
				The default value.
			</description>
		</entry>
		<entry name ="Inlet 4 (float/llll)">
			<description>
				Lambda inlet.
				A lambda inlet is an inlet receiving the answer from a test or modification performed on elements sent out the lambda outlets. <br />
				In this case, the answer is expected to be a modification of the elements which had been sent out:
				the element output via the lambda outlet can be customly modified and then plugged in into this lambda inlet:
				such modification will be accounted for by the algorithm. <br />
				The lambda inlet also accepts the result in llll form, so you can sometimes avoid the explicit @out t. <br />
				It is important to know that the evaluation chain inside the lambda loop must be direct: you can't use objects such as <o>delay</o>,
				<o>pipe</o>, <o>defer</o>; nor store the value anywhere waiting for some other event to trigger it. Also see #lambda in the bach Help Center.
				<br /> <br />
			</description>
		</entry>
	</misc>

	<misc name = "Output">
		<entry name ="Outlet 1 (list)">
			<description>
				The messages for <o>line~</o>.
			</description>
		</entry>
		<entry name ="Outlet 2 (llll)">
			<description>
				Lambda outlet.
				A lambda outlet is an outlet outputting an element on which some test or modification must be performed.
				The result of the test or modification is then expected in a lambda inlet. <br />
				In this case, the elements output from the lambda outlet may be customly modified, so that such modification will be taken into
				account by the algorithm. To modify each element, just use patching and then plug into the lambda inlet the
				modified version of the element. <br />
				It is important to know that the evaluation chain inside the lambda loop must be direct: you can't use objects such as <o>delay</o>,
				<o>pipe</o>, <o>defer</o>; nor store the value anywhere waiting for some other event to trigger it. Also see #lambda in the bach Help Center.
				<br /> <br />
			</description>
		</entry>
	</misc>

</c74object>