<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="./_c74_ref.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!--This file has been automatically generated by Doctor Max. DO NOT EDIT THIS FILE DIRECTLY.-->

<c74object name="bach.tierev" module="bach" kind="patcher">

	<digest>
		Reverse a sequence of ties
	</digest>

	<description>
		Accepts in its left inlet an llll of pitches, in its right inlet an llll ties,
	</description>

	<!--METADATA-->
	<metadatalist>
		<metadata name="author">bachproject</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">bach</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">bach abstractions</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">bach notation</metadata>
	</metadatalist>

	<!--INLETS-->
	<inletlist>
		<inlet id="0" type="INLET_TYPE">
			<digest>
				The llll containing reference pitches
			</digest>
			<description>
			</description>
		</inlet>
		<inlet id="1" type="INLET_TYPE">
			<digest>
				The llll containing ties information
			</digest>
			<description>
			</description>
		</inlet>
	</inletlist>

	<!--OUTLETS-->
	<outletlist>
		<outlet id="0" type="INLET_TYPE">
			<digest>
				The properly reversed ties llll
			</digest>
			<description>
			</description>
		</outlet>
	</outletlist>

	<!--ARGUMENTS-->
	<objarglist>
	</objarglist>

	<!--MESSAGES-->
	<methodlist>
		<method name="bang">
			<arglist />
			<digest>
				Reverse the ties llll
			</digest>
			<description>
				Performs the operation on most recently received input lllls.
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="llll">
			<arglist />
			<digest>
				Set reference pitches or ties llll, output result
			</digest>
			<description>
				An llll in the first inlet is considered as the llll containing pitches (in midicents),
				and will reverse the ties llll and output the result. <br />
				An llll in the second inlet is considered as the llll containing tie information, structured exactly
				as pitches llll (1 for notes starting a tie, 0 otherwise). Such ties llll will be the one to be
				reversed and output when the reference pitches llll is received in the first inlet. <br />
				The two lllls must have the same structure, and can either be chord-wise lllls (one list for each chord,
				one element for each note), or voice-wise lllls (one list for each voice, one list for each chord,
				one element for each note).
			</description>
		</method>
	</methodlist>

	<!--ATTRIBUTES-->
	<attributelist>
		<attribute name="out" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1">
			<digest>
				Outlet Types
			</digest>
			<description>
				The <m>out</m> attribute is a sequence of characters identifying the outlet types (one character for each llll outlet). Characters can be one of the following: <br />
				<m>n</m> (default): 'native' output: faster and more precise between bach objects, but unreadable by standard Max objects (an "bach.llll" message appears instead). <br />
				<m>t</m>: 'text' output: slower and limited in size, but readable by standard Max objects. A plain llll in text format is a generic Max message.
				To keep the representation invertible (i.e., to allow a bach object receiving a text-format llll to interpret it exactly as if it was native format,
				except for the size limitation), some specific kinds of symbols are preceded by a backtick: namely, symbols containing parens, or containing textual
				representations of numbers or pitches, or beginning with a backtick, plus the symbols "null" and "nil" (distinct from the reserved words
				"null" and "nil" representing the empty list and the empty sublist) are preceded by a backtick. Moreover, the symbols "int", "float" or "list"
				are preceded by a backtick only if they are the first element of an llll, to distinguish them from the corresponding reserved messages of Max. <br />
				<m>m</m>: 'max' output: mostly equivalent to the "t" specifier, but no symbol is backticket except "int", "float" and "list" at the beginning of an llll.
				It is important to notice that, differently from text-format lllls proper, Max-format lllls might not be invertible even if they do not reach the size
				limit for Max message. This means that a bach object receiving a Max-format llll output from another bach object might interpret it differently
				from the original, or in some cases might even reject it. <br />
				<m>x</m>: disabled output (nothing is output) <br />
				<m>p</m>: 'portal' output: only used by bach.portal to intercept the @out attribute specified while creating the abstraction (see bach.portal). <br />
				The native output is recommended, unless communication with standard Max messages is needed.
				Disabling unused outputs can be useful if extreme optimization of the patch is needed.
				<br /> <br />
			</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="category" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="Behavior" />
				<attribute name="label" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="Outlet Types" />
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="text" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
	</attributelist>

	<!--DISCUSSION-->
	<discussion>
		<o>bach.tierev</o> accepts either a chord-wise sequence of pitches and ties,
	</discussion>

	<!--SEEALSO-->
	<seealsolist>
		<seealso name="bach.chordrev" />
		<seealso name="bach.chordrot" />
		<seealso name="bach.restrot" />
		<seealso name="bach.fromc&amp;r" />
		<seealso name="bach.toc&amp;r" />
		<seealso name="bach.score" />
		<seealso name="04-Through The Looking Glass" module="bach" type="tutorial" />
	</seealsolist>

	<misc name = "Input">
		<entry name ="Inlet 1 (llll)">
			<description>
				The llll containing reference pitches.
			</description>
		</entry>
		<entry name ="Inlet 2 (llll)">
			<description>
				The llll containing ties information.
			</description>
		</entry>
	</misc>

	<misc name = "Output">
		<entry name ="Outlet 1 (llll)">
			<description>
				The properly reversed ties llll.
			</description>
		</entry>
	</misc>

	<misc name = "Discussion">
		<entry name ="More details">
			<description>
		<o>bach.tierev</o> accepts either a chord-wise sequence of pitches and ties,
			</description>
		</entry>
		<entry name ="Keywords">
			<description>
reverse, tie, sequence, chord, pitch, voice.
			</description>
		</entry>
	</misc>

</c74object>