<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="./_c74_ref.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!--This file has been automatically generated by Doctor Max. DO NOT EDIT THIS FILE DIRECTLY.-->

<c74object name="bach.pick" module="bach">

	<digest>
		Return elements from an llll
	</digest>

	<description>
		<o>bach.pick</o> returns one or more elements from an llll, according to their positions.
	</description>

	<!--METADATA-->
	<metadatalist>
		<metadata name="author">bachproject</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">bach</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">bach objects</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">bach llll</metadata>
	</metadatalist>

	<!--INLETS-->
	<inletlist>
		<inlet id="0" type="INLET_TYPE">
			<digest>
				llll to extract elements from
			</digest>
			<description>
			</description>
		</inlet>
	</inletlist>

	<!--OUTLETS-->
	<outletlist>
		<outlet id="0" type="INLET_TYPE">
			<digest>
				Extracted elements
			</digest>
			<description>
			</description>
		</outlet>
	</outletlist>

	<!--ARGUMENTS-->
	<objarglist>
		<objarg name="addresses" optional="0" type="llll">
			<digest>
				Addresses of the elements to extract
			</digest>
			<description>
				The addresses of the elements to extract from the incoming llll.
				An address is an llll providing a unique representation of the position of an element in another llll.
				It is a concept shared by many bach object.
				The address of each element of an llll's root level is simply its position counting from 1.
				The address of an element in a sublist is a list composed by the position of the element in the sublist,
				preceded by the position of the sublist in the parent llll,
				and so on up to the root level, as a sort of "path" to the element.<br />
				For instance, given the llll <b>a b c (d e (f g) h i) j k</b> the position of <b>c</b> is <b>3</b>;
				the position of <b>(d e (f g) h i)</b> is <b>4</b>;
				the position if <b>e</b> is <b>4 2</b> since to reach it it takes to go to the 4th element of the root level, which is a sublist,
				and to the 2nd element of that sublist.
				By reading the address from right to left, it can be seen that this is equivalent to saying
				that the pointed element is the 2nd of the 4th.
				Likewise, in the above llll <b>f</b> has the address <b>4 3 1</b> since it is the 1st of the 3rd of the 4th.<br />
				In addition, addresses sent to bach objects can contain negative positions,
				that is positions counted from the end of the llll instead than the right.
				Negative and positive positions can be safely mixed within a single address.
				Thus, the address of the element <b>g</b> can be expressed as <b>4 3 2</b> as well as <b>4 3 -1</b> or <b>-3 -3 -1</b>.<br />
				Each address should be wrapped in parentheses, unless it refers to an element in the root level of the llll,
				in which case the single index by which it is composed can be left unparenthesized.
				For each specified address an outlet is created.<br />
				For example, <m>(1 2) (3 4)</m> will create two outlets, one for the <m>1 2</m> address, the other for the <m>3 4</m> address.<br/>
				<m>1 2 (3 4)</m> will create three outlets, respectively for the <m>1</m>, <m>2</m> and <m>3 4</m> addresses:
				that is, it is equivalent to writing <m>(1) (2) (3 4)</m>.
			</description>
		</objarg>
	</objarglist>

	<!--MESSAGES-->
	<methodlist>
		<method name="llll">
			<arglist />
			<digest>
				Return specified elements
			</digest>
			<description>
			</description>
		</method>
	</methodlist>

	<!--ATTRIBUTES-->
	<attributelist>
		<attribute name="nullmode" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1">
			<digest>
				Output Null
			</digest>
			<description>
				When set to 1, <b>null</b> is output from any outlet corresponding to a non-existing element in the input llll.
			</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="label" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="Output Null" />
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="onoff" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="out" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1">
			<digest>
				Outlet Types
			</digest>
			<description>
				The <m>out</m> attribute is a sequence of characters identifying the outlet types (one character for each llll outlet). Characters can be one of the following: <br />
				<m>n</m> (default): 'native' output: faster and more precise between bach objects, but unreadable by standard Max objects (an "bach.llll" message appears instead). <br />
				<m>t</m>: 'text' output: slower and limited in size, but readable by standard Max objects. A plain llll in text format is a generic Max message.
				To keep the representation invertible (i.e., to allow a bach object receiving a text-format llll to interpret it exactly as if it was native format,
				except for the size limitation), some specific kinds of symbols are preceded by a backtick: namely, symbols containing parens, or containing textual
				representations of numbers or pitches, or beginning with a backtick, plus the symbols "null" and "nil" (distinct from the reserved words
				"null" and "nil" representing the empty list and the empty sublist) are preceded by a backtick. Moreover, the symbols "int", "float" or "list"
				are preceded by a backtick only if they are the first element of an llll, to distinguish them from the corresponding reserved messages of Max. <br />
				<m>m</m>: 'max' output: mostly equivalent to the "t" specifier, but no symbol is backticket except "int", "float" and "list" at the beginning of an llll.
				It is important to notice that, differently from text-format lllls proper, Max-format lllls might not be invertible even if they do not reach the size
				limit for Max message. This means that a bach object receiving a Max-format llll output from another bach object might interpret it differently
				from the original, or in some cases might even reject it. <br />
				<m>x</m>: disabled output (nothing is output) <br />
				<m>p</m>: 'portal' output: only used by bach.portal to intercept the @out attribute specified while creating the abstraction (see bach.portal). <br />
				The native output is recommended, unless communication with standard Max messages is needed.
				Disabling unused outputs can be useful if extreme optimization of the patch is needed.
				<br /> <br />
			</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="category" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="Behavior" />
				<attribute name="label" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="Outlet Types" />
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="text" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="unwrap" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1">
			<digest>
				Unwrap
			</digest>
			<description>
				When set to 1 (default), the outermost couple of parentheses of any sublist to be output is removed.
				For instance, if the llll <b>a b (c d e)</b> is input and its third element is requested,
				<b>c d e</b> will be output instead of <b>(c d e)</b>.
			</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="label" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="Unwrap" />
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="onoff" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
	</attributelist>

	<!--SEEALSO-->
	<seealsolist>
		<seealso name="bach.nth" />
		<seealso name="bach.keys" />
	</seealsolist>

	<misc name = "Input">
		<entry name ="Inlet 1 (llll)">
			<description>
				llll to extract elements from.
			</description>
		</entry>
	</misc>

	<misc name = "Output">
		<entry name ="Outlets 1, 2, 3...">
			<description>
				Extracted elements.
			</description>
		</entry>
	</misc>

</c74object>