<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="./_c74_ref.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!--This file has been automatically generated by Doctor Max. DO NOT EDIT THIS FILE DIRECTLY.-->

<c74object name="bach.textin" module="bach">

	<digest>
		Accept variants of the llll text format
	</digest>

	<description>
		Parses lllls according to variants of the text format.
	</description>

	<!--METADATA-->
	<metadatalist>
		<metadata name="author">bachproject</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">bach</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">bach objects</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">bach llll</metadata>
	</metadatalist>

	<!--INLETS-->
	<inletlist>
		<inlet id="0" type="INLET_TYPE">
			<digest>
				llll to be interpreted according to the <m>ignore</m> attribute and output from the corresponding outlet
			</digest>
			<description>
			</description>
		</inlet>
	</inletlist>

	<!--OUTLETS-->
	<outletlist>
		<outlet id="0" type="INLET_TYPE">
			<digest>
				The llll received in the corresponding inlet
			</digest>
			<description>
			</description>
		</outlet>
	</outletlist>

	<!--ARGUMENTS-->
	<objarglist>
		<objarg name="inlets" optional="1" type="int">
			<digest>
				Number of llll inlets/outlets
			</digest>
			<description>
			</description>
		</objarg>
	</objarglist>

	<!--MESSAGES-->
	<methodlist>
		<method name="llll">
			<arglist />
			<digest>
				A text-format llll received in any inlet
			</digest>
			<description>
			</description>
		</method>
	</methodlist>

	<!--ATTRIBUTES-->
	<attributelist>
		<attribute name="ignore" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1">
			<digest>
				
			</digest>
			<description>
				The <m>ignore</m> attribute allows preventing certain categories
				of elements to be interpreted according to the usual bach syntax.
				Categories are expressed by letters, according to the following table:<br />
				- <b>L</b> stands for all the open and closed parens marking llll sublists:
				if this category is set, parens and symbols containing parens
				are interpreted just as symbols, as if they were preceded by a backtick. <br />
				- <b>l</b> stands for open and closed parens marking llll sublists,
				only if they do not appear in a symbol of their own
				(i.e., with the <b>l</b> category set,
				<b>(</b> is interpreted as the beginning of a sublist,
				whereas <b>(1</b> is interpreted just as a plain symbol,
				as opposed to what would happen normally,
				when it would mark the beginning of a sublist
				whose first element is <b>1</b>). <br />
				- <b>r</b> stands for rationals. <br />
				- <b>p</b> stands for pitches. <br />
				- <b>e</b> stands for floating-point numbers in scientific notation. <br />
				- <b>s</b> stands for the special symbols <b>nil</b> and <b>null</b>. <br />
				- <b>b</b> causes symbols beginning with a backtick
				to be interpreted with the backtick included
				(e.g., the <b>`foo</b> symbol is read as it is, including the backtick,
				as opposed to what would happen normally, when it would be read as <b>foo</b>). <br />
				- <b>a</b> stands for ignoring all the above categories.
				If it is present alongside other specifiers (e.g., <b>alp</b>), it overrides them. <br />
				- <b>-</b> stands for no category, and it is the default.
				If it is present alongside other specifiers (e.g., <b>-p</b>), it is ignored. <br />
				For example, the <m>ignore</m> attribute could be set to <b>lp</b>,
				which would cause a message containing <b>( a001 Mahler(Bernstein).aif )</b>
				to be interpreted as an llll containing a sublist,
				containing in turn the symbols <b>a001</b> and <b>Mahler(Bernstein).aif</b>.
				Without setting the <m>ignore</m> attribute, the same message would be interpreted
				as an llll containing a sublist containing the pitch <b>A1</b>,
				the symbol <b>Mahler</b>,
				a further sublist only containing the symbol <b>Bernstein</b>,
				and finally the symbol <b>.aif</b>. <br />
			</description>
			<attributelist>
				<attribute name="style" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1" value="text" />
			</attributelist>
		</attribute>
	</attributelist>

	<!--SEEALSO-->
	<seealsolist>
		<seealso name="bach.portal" />
		<seealso name="bach.textout" />
		<seealso name="bach.read" />
	</seealsolist>

	<misc name = "Input">
		<entry name ="Inlets 1, 2, 3... (llll)">
			<description>
				llll to be interpreted according to the <m>ignore</m> attribute and output from the corresponding outlet.
			</description>
		</entry>
	</misc>

	<misc name = "Output">
		<entry name ="Outlet 1 (llll)">
			<description>
				The llll received in the corresponding inlet.
			</description>
		</entry>
	</misc>

</c74object>